<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The boy of Bilson: or, A true discouery of the late notorious impostures of certaine Romish priests in their pretended exorcisme, or expulsion of the Diuell out of a young boy, named William Perry, sonne of Thomas Perry of Bilson, in the county of Stafford, yeoman Vpon which occasion, hereunto is premitted a briefe theologicall discourse, by way of caution, for the more easie discerning of such Romish spirits; and iudging of their false pretences, both in this and the like practices.</title>
            <author>R. B. (Richard Baddeley)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68096</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1185</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120841</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856034</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856034</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21548</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68096)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21548)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 651:1, 1565:3, 1616:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The boy of Bilson: or, A true discouery of the late notorious impostures of certaine Romish priests in their pretended exorcisme, or expulsion of the Diuell out of a young boy, named William Perry, sonne of Thomas Perry of Bilson, in the county of Stafford, yeoman Vpon which occasion, hereunto is premitted a briefe theologicall discourse, by way of caution, for the more easie discerning of such Romish spirits; and iudging of their false pretences, both in this and the like practices.</title>
                  <author>R. B. (Richard Baddeley)</author>
                  <author>Wheeler, Mr.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 47, [1], 45-75, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by F[elix] K[ingston] for William Barret,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the Christian reader" signed: Ryc. Baddeley.</note>
                  <note>A reprinting of and reply to "A faithfull relation of the proceedings of the Catholicke gentlemen with the boy of Bilson" attributed to a Mr. Wheeler, of which no copy survives.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the originals in Cambridge University Library, the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, and the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 651 (Cambridge University Library copy), at reel 1565 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy), and at reel 1616 (British Library copy).</note>
                  <note>Reel 651: some pages missed in filming. Reel 1565: some print show-through; an improved filming over reel 651.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wheeler, --  Mr.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Demoniac possession --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Exorcism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21548:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21548:1"/>
            <p>THE BOY OF BILSON: OR, A TRVE DISCOVERY OF THE LATE NOTORIOVS IM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POSTVRES OF CERTAINE ROMISH <hi>Prieſts</hi> in their pretended <hi>Exorciſme,</hi> or expulſion of <hi>the Diuell out of a young Boy, named</hi> WILLIAM PERRY, <hi>ſonne of</hi> THOMAS PERRY <hi>of</hi> Bilſon, <hi>in the County of</hi> Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, <hi>Yeoman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon which occaſion, hereunto is premitted <hi>A briefe Theologicall Diſcourſe, by way of Caution,</hi> for the more eaſie diſcerning of ſuch Romiſh ſpirits; and iudging of their falſe pretences, both in this and the like Practices.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. Theſ. 2.10, 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Becauſe they receiued not the loue of the truth, that they might be ſaued. For this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſion, that they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue a lye.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>F. K.</hi> for <hi>William Barret.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21548:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21548:2"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing acquainted with the mind and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the <hi>Author</hi> of this enſuing <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,</hi> and hauing thereunto added thoſe other Pieces (vnto which I am no ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,) to make the <hi>Narration</hi> complete, as concerning <hi>the Boy of Bilſon:</hi> I thought it my duty, after much ſollicitation, to communicate the whole in print; and ſo to make it <hi>iuris publici.</hi> And this (as I thought) theſe very times did exact. For now the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts haue ſo cauterized their conſciences, and rub'd their foreheads, as that they take delight, and bluſh not, daily to forge and coyne most monstrous<note n="*" place="margin">Witnes (among many others) their freſh <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-lye,</hi> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſuppoſed <hi>Apoſtaſie</hi> of the late <hi>L. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths; all to ſupport their drooping and dropping Cauſe. Since therefore their appetites are ſo well <hi>whetted</hi> and ſet on edge (by what<note n="*" place="margin">Perhaps the ſame that one of them hanged about the Boyes necke. <hi>vid.</hi> pag. <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Stone</hi> we may eaſily gheſſe, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their due reward,) as that they make no bones of whatſoeuer is ſet before them; to ſtay their ſtomacks a while, let them be chewing this bit, (which otherwiſe they ſhall not now eſchue,) <hi>Vt quam falſa dicendo</hi> &amp; ſcrthendo <hi>voluptatem ceperint, eandem vera</hi> legendo &amp; <hi>audiendo amittant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then (good Reader) in the first place thou hast a <hi>Treatiſe</hi> profeſſedly written for a <hi>Diſcouery</hi> of, and a <hi>Caution</hi> against the enueagling proiects of Romiſh <hi>Prieſts,</hi> chiefly in that one particular, <hi>viz.</hi> their preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Priestly <hi>Exorcizing</hi> and expolling <hi>of Diuels</hi> out of bodies poſſeſſed. By which thou maiſt iudge, whether theſe <hi>Mirabularies</hi> deſerue not the reputation of the
<pb facs="tcp:21548:3"/>varest <hi>Mountebanks</hi> of theſe times. Next followes, <hi>A faithfull Relation</hi> (for ſo they name it) made by theſe <hi>Prieſts, touching</hi> their <hi>proceedings with the Boy:</hi> which they did purpoſely write and diſperſe,<note place="margin">Vide pag. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>To the end</hi> (as they profeſſe) <hi>that all indifferent mindes may magnifie and praiſe Almighty God, that hath left ſuch power to men, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q> ſuch (for ſooth) as they had, in <hi>Exorcizing</hi> and coniuring the <hi>Diuell</hi> within that <hi>Boy,</hi> being their ſuppoſed deſperate <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack.</hi> Which glorious worke of theirs when theſe <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Aruſpices</hi> ſhall, at their next enteruiew, recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize,<note place="margin">cie.</note> 
               <hi>Mirabor ſi non riſerint.</hi> And that ſo much the rather, after they haue peruſed the Remaine of this Booke, in which the Euent and ſucceſſe of the whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is truly related; and their formidable <hi>Mormo</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued no other then an Apiſh <hi>Cobalus.</hi> Whereby it will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo come to paſſe that theſe <hi>Catholike Gentlemen</hi> (for ſo they ſtile the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, albeit by their<note n="*" place="margin">See their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions in this Booke. pag. <hi>63.64.</hi> &amp;c.</note> outward garbe one would rather ſuſpect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Serning-men &amp; attendants on ſuch perſons, <hi>nè quid grauius</hi>) ſhall be ſo cleerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced of palpable Quackſaluing, as that a very meane Herald, knowing the houſe they come of, may blazon their Armes; and ſo expoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto ſhame and laughter.</p>
            <p>But I will not intertaine thee (gentle Reader) with any longer parle in the entrance, after that I ſhall put thee in mind of that ſound aduiſe, which an Heathen Philoſopher long ſince preſcribed (but neuer ſo neceſſary as now, when Popiſh impostures are ſo rife,) <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Ipicharmus.</note> Which may be thus engliſhed; <hi>Bee wiſe, and bee not haſty to beleeue.</hi> which precious <hi>Amulet</hi> I commend vnto thee, and All of vs to the rich mercy of our moſt gracious God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ryc. Baddeley.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21548:3"/>
            <head>THE GENERALL HEADS of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. A Diſcourſe, by way of Caution, concerning Popiſh Exorcizing of vncleane ſpirits. Pag. 1</item>
               <item>II. A Relation made by certaine Romiſh Prieſts, and by one of them diſperſed; wherein they magnifie the power of their Exorciſme ouer the diuell, in the Boy of Bilſon. Pag. 41</item>
               <item>III. A deſcription of the admirable guile and cunning of that Boy, in counterfeiting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe poſſeſſed of the diuell. Pag. 55</item>
               <item>IV. The meanes and manner vſed by the R. Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God THOMAS Lo. Biſhop of Couentry and Lichfield, for diſcouering his diſſimulation. Pag. 56</item>
               <item>V. The two examinations of the Boy, taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Reuerend Father; together with his plaine and direct Confeſſion of the whole Complot and Practice. Pag. 61, 69</item>
               <item>VI. The Succeſſe and euent of all, ſhewed in the Boyes (firſt) priuate, and (after) publike Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement made before the whole County, in the Summer-Aſſizes held at Stafford this preſent yeere 1621. Pag. 72</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:21548:4"/>
            <head>Faults eſcaped in ſome Copies.</head>
            <p>Pag. 14. lin. 2. reade, <hi>will you ſo.</hi> p. 25. l. 11. r. <hi>the third poynt.</hi> p. 28. l. 14. r. <hi>Adiuration.</hi> p. 33. l. 6. r. <hi>to prooue.</hi> Beſides, mend the numbers of the Pages, in the letters E. H. I.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21548:4"/>
            <head>A DISCOVRSE CONCERNING <hi>Popiſh Exorcizing.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
               <hi>Miracle</hi> being (as Diuine learning doth teach) a Worke of Omnipotencie, farre excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all naturall power of any Creature, is the <hi>broad Seale</hi> of Almightie <hi>God,</hi> for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of Truth: which whoſoeuer ſhall dare to counterfeit, muſt needs be guiltie of no leſſe then high Treaſon againſt the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Majeſtie. Neceſſarily therefore will it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, as in ſpeciall thoſe that take vpon them the Office of working <hi>Miracles</hi> in theſe times, to feare and tremble at ſuch dangerous impietie; ſo alſo in generall euery Chriſtian and religious Soule to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, that he be not circumvented by any forgerie in this kind, and thereby drawne to admire and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme, as the <hi>finger of God,</hi> the lewd and ridiculous iuglings of wretched men. For which end I haue aduentured to ſet downe certayne Aduertiſements, whereby others may bee reaſonably directed how to diſcouer &amp; auoid ſuch kind of Popiſh deluſions.</p>
            <div n="1" type="advertisement">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21548:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The firſt Aduertiſement;</hi> Againſt a falſe Propoſition of the Romaniſts, who make the vſe of <hi>Miracles</hi> to be a perpetuall and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie note of the Catholike Church.</head>
               <p>THe Propoſition much inſiſted vpon and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>Bellarmine, Coſter, Valentian,</hi> and other <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> is, that <hi>the vſe of Miracles is a neceſſarie, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall, and proſitable Character and Note of the true Church of Chriſt,</hi> aſwell in theſe Times as it was in the Dayes of the <hi>Apostles.</hi> This we are warranted to call a falſe Propoſition. Firſt, becauſe that <hi>Gift</hi> cannot bee called <hi>perpetuall,</hi> which ceaſed by little and little;<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Aug.</note> inſomuch that Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and Saint <hi>Augustine,</hi> could ſay of their owne times (which bordered neare vpon the Dayes of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church) that diuers kind of <hi>Apostolicall Miracles</hi> were then <hi>ceaſed.</hi> How much leſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can this Power bee expected in theſe latter Times, of which the Romaniſts owne Biſhop (who Rued in the dayes of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, and whom they haue magnified with the Title of a <hi>Martyr,</hi> that is, a <hi>Witneſſe</hi> of the Truth) did auouch, ſaying,<note place="margin">Ich. Roffenſ. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcop. cor. Luth. de Capt. Bab. c. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The promiſe of God touching Miracles, God would not haue to be perpetuall in his Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, if they were <hi>neceſſarie</hi> (eſpecially) for the confirmation of the Doctrines of Faith, as the Romiſh Prieſts doe in their <hi>Exorciſmes</hi> profeſſe; then would not S. <hi>Gregorie,</hi> the firſt and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Pope of that name, haue held them neceſſarie onely for the firſt begetting, breeding, and nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21548:5"/>of the Church:<note place="margin">Greg. hom. <hi>49.</hi> in Euang.</note> 
                  <hi>Euen as</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the watering of plants is neceſſary, when they are firſt planted, which, after they be come to growth, will be of no vſe.</hi> Which ſentence of S. <hi>Gregorie,</hi> did peraduenture draw the like Aſſertion from the quill of the Ieſuit <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Delrio Icſ. Diſq. Mag. Tem. <hi>2.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> ſaying (although ſomewhat mincing it) <hi>For the eſtabliſhing of the Faith, there is now little neceſsitie of Miracles, or none at all.</hi> But more thorrowly their ſaid Biſhop, who holdeth them not neceſſarie, but <hi>for the time of the birth and breeding of the Church.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Roffenſ. ſup.</note> Whereunto (to forbeare any further ſearch after Witneſſes) their Ieſuit <hi>Acosta</hi> accordeth;<note place="margin">Acoſta Ieſ. de ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut. Iudor. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>There being a difference</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>betweene the primitiue Times and theſe Dayes wherein we liue, for what need we any confirmation by Miracles?</hi> So he.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, touching the <hi>profitableneſſe of Miratles</hi> in the latter Ages of the World, Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> durſt ſay, that <hi>it is more profitable to want them;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> as hee is alleaged by <hi>Acoſta. ibid. c.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>it being a matter of greater worthineſſe to beleeue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them.</hi> Yea, their owne Preacher, entring into this contemplation, taught publikely,<note place="margin">Stella in Lue. <hi>11</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>Miracles now would be rather an hindrance vnto Faith.</hi> And I cannot beleeue he ſpake without booke, ſeeing that our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt</hi> (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth) <hi>hath giuen vs a caution,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. Tract. <hi>13.</hi> in loh. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>againſt</hi> theſe <hi>Miracle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 13.5.</note> 
                  <hi>willing vs to take heede that we be not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi> Whereof their Ieſuit will giue vs ſome reaſon, euen,<note place="margin">Acoſta Ieſ. de temp. nouiſſ. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe that in the time of Antichriſt it will bee hard to diſcerne true Miracles from falſe.</hi> Where then ſhall a Chriſtian caſt Anchor in ſo great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſeducement by <hi>Antichriſtian Miracles?</hi> the true anſwere to this will giue vs full ſatisfaction;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21548:6"/>and this wee haue confeſſed by the mouth of the ſame Ieſuit, as abſolutely as any Proteſtant can profeſſe.<note place="margin">Acoſla ibid. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Our ſtrongest hold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>must be the holy Scriptures, which are of more ſtrength than any Miracles: nor can the Seruant of Chriſt haue a ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Fort againſt the power of Antichriſt.</hi> Which Tenet, concerning the ſecuritie of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> by <hi>Scriptures,</hi> was anciently held before the dayes of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> as we reade in the ancient <hi>Authour of the worke,</hi> paſſing vnder the name of S. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hom. <hi>49.</hi> in Matth.</note> 
                  <hi>True Chriſtians</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>were diſcerned in former times by Miracles, but now by Scriptures.</hi> This is the Fort which will defend vs, and therefore we aboue all things ought to defend it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſecond Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing the falſe Aſſumption of the Romaniſts, in challenging to themſelues the power of <hi>Miracles,</hi> as a perpetuall gift peculiarly belonging to their Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Church.</head>
               <p>ALthough the Ieſuit <hi>Turſelline</hi> talketh and boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of many maruelous <hi>Miracles,</hi> daily done in <hi>Italy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hiſt. Domus Lauret.</note> 
                  <hi>Which</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>are no leſſe glorious than thoſe miracles in the dayes of old:</hi> yet doubt we not to call this <hi>Aſſumption</hi> a meerely vaine preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For if wee require them to ſhew vs in their Church the power of <hi>Prophecie,</hi> they might take (I thinke) a Lanterne to ſeeke thorowout all <hi>Italy,</hi> and not find any one whom they can point out to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21548:6"/>bee profeſſedly a <hi>Prophet.</hi> If we inquire after the <hi>gift of Tongues,</hi> to ſpeake ſtrange languages, where can they ſhew this? Miracles (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>are for vnbeleeuers,</hi> or <hi>Infidels:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.22.</note> and no <hi>Miracle</hi> more neceſſarie for the conuerſion of <hi>Infidels</hi> in the <hi>Indies</hi> than to be able to ſpeak the languages of thoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, becauſe <hi>Faith commeth by hearing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 10.17. 1. Cor. 14.</note> and <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a knowne language.</hi> Yet wee know that the Prieſts, who daily labour for the conuerſion of thoſe <hi>Infidels,</hi> confeſſe that they are glad to labour and ſtudie Moneths and Yeares, to learne the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages of thoſe Countries.</p>
               <p>But, to ſpeake more generally, How can this be ſaid to be a <hi>perpetuall Badge</hi> of the Roman Church, whereof a famous Biſhop (liuing but about foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeares ſince) being poſed by <hi>Luther,</hi> to ſhew in all <hi>Europe</hi> where there was any that could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe himſelf endowed with that <hi>Gift;</hi> anſwered plainly,<note place="margin">Roffenſ. in Luth. de Capt. Babyl. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> and without any Parable (ſpeaking of the power of <hi>Miracles) Cuius</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>effectum nunc nullum cernimus: Whereof wee ſee no effect in our dayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When wee further inſiſt, and aske, concerning this great ſigne of the ordinarie worke of <hi>Miracles,</hi> where this <hi>Starre</hi> doth appeare? ſurely, not at their <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the Citie of <hi>Rome;</hi> nor yet in <hi>Europe,</hi> their <hi>Iurie,</hi> for they ſend vs to ſeeke it in the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found World, in the conuerſion of <hi>Pagans;</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing (as it may ſeeme) and that iuſtly with their <hi>Eſpencaeus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſpen. in <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>3</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>Miracles are no where neceſſarie, but among Infidels.</hi> Here then, if any where, we are to ſeeke it, to wit, in the <hi>Indies;</hi> where behold <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21548:7"/>and their other <hi>Magi</hi> doe ſee it <hi>riſing</hi> (as it were) in the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> and ſetting in the <hi>Weſt-Indies.</hi> No queſtion therefore, but wee are like to find it in thoſe <hi>Indies;</hi> that which is their ordinarie <hi>Aſſumption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For confutation whereof we need not to trauell ſo farre, to trie this; two famous <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> who haue beene moſt conuerſant there, and taken (as is ſaid) moſt paines for the conuerting of <hi>Infidels</hi> to the Faith of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> come vnto vs by their Bookes, and tell vs, the one, that this <hi>Aſſumption</hi> is falſe, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though auouched by them, yet not ſaying that it is true. For of the Eaſt Indies, their Ieſuit <hi>Acoſta</hi> ſaith aſſeuerantly;<note place="margin">Acoſta Icſ. de ſalute Indor. l. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Prodigia nulla facimus, ſigna nulla edimus: We worke no Wonders, we ſhew no Miracles.</hi> In the Weſt Indies, who more reſident than their Ieſuite <hi>Xauier,</hi> whom they report to haue beene their <hi>Thaumaturgus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ballar. l. <hi>4.</hi> de Not is Eccleſ. c. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>to haue bealed lame, dumbe, deafe, blind, yea and to haue raiſed the dead to life.</hi> Notwithſtanding, when wee conſult with <hi>Francis Xauier</hi> himſelfe, in his Volume of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſlles,</hi> directed vnto the <hi>Fathers</hi> of his owne <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> vnto <hi>Cardinals,</hi> and others of beſt eſteeme; hee maketh no mention there of theſe <hi>miraculous works.</hi> Which wee doubt not but hee would haue done, if any ſuch Acts had beene wrought. For we may not thinke that Ieſuites would profeſſe more modeſtie, in this kind, than the holy <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> who, to the glorie of God, and comfort of his Church, did profeſſe to reueale and report (ſpeaking of their Miracles) <hi>Magnalia Dei; The wondrous works of God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.11.</note> Therefore we take this his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21548:7"/>not verifying the report of his Miracles, ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſuggeſted, and ſo greedily intertayned by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to amount to no leſſe than the deniall of them to be true.</p>
               <p>Let me adde vnto <hi>Francis Xauier</hi> their <hi>Francis de Victoria,</hi> Profeſſor of Diuinitie in <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Fra. de Vict. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. <hi>5.</hi> ſect. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſing this great point, whether that the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſt</hi> were ſo ſufficiently reuealed vnto the <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels</hi> of theſe times, <hi>by Word,</hi> or <hi>Miracles,</hi> that they, which would not bee conuerted, mightiuſtly bee condemned of ſo vnpardonable obſtinacie, as to deſerue to bee perſecuted by Sword; after his deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate and earneſt ſearch to ſatisfie himſelfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in this, anſwereth (concerning Miracles) <hi>Signa nulla audio: I heare of no Miracles.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The third Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing that it hath beene a cuſtome among Romiſh Prieſts, willingly to deceiue the people by counterfeit Acts and Reports.</head>
               <p>HOw ſhall this bee newes to Any, who hath beene acquainted with ſome of their owne Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors? One confeſſing,<note place="margin">Lyrain Dam.</note> that <hi>People are deceiued by falſe miracles, deuiſed by Prieſts, and ſuch as adhere vnto them.</hi> A ſecond,<note place="margin">Melchior Canus loc. Theol.</note> 
                  <hi>remembring</hi> (as hee himſelfe ſaith) <hi>with griefe ſome Hiſtorians, abuſing the credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the people, by relating the miracles of Saints.</hi> A third inueighing againſt the prodigalitie of ſome vaine <hi>Reports of falſe miracles.</hi> A fourth,<note place="margin">Eraſ. ante lib. Conſeſſ. Aug.</note> and alſo a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21548:8"/>fift partly <hi>ſcorning,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Agrippa de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. ſcient. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iucs in Aug. de Ciuit. Dei, l. <hi>22.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> and partly <hi>abborring</hi> their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous relations, and vaine forgeries of <hi>Miracles.</hi> Theſe confeſſions may ſetue for the preſent.</p>
               <p>We need not be inquiſitiue into Examples fetcth from other Countries, concerning the iuggling tricks of the <hi>Friars</hi> of former times, which haue beene detected to their ſhame; nor yet of a late<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſtoire admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable de la poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion d'vne Penitente, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duite par vn Magicien, &amp;c. conduite a la S. Baume poury eſtre exorcizee, l'An <hi>1610.</hi> ſoubz l'autorite du R.P. F. Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlien Michaelis, Prieur de couent Royal de la S. Magdaleine a S. Maximin, &amp;c. A la Reyne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente, Paris <hi>1613.</hi> auec pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilege du Roy. <hi>It was tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall Copie, by W.B. and printed,</hi> Anno <hi>1613. which Edition is here after obſerued. Printed,</hi> Anno Domini <hi>1603.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Hiſtorie</hi> (as they call it) of notable <hi>Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſmes,</hi> performed at Saint <hi>Baume</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> which will hereafter bewray it ſelfe by its owne contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: becauſe our owne halfe Iſle, euen little <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> will be found to abound as much with varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of falſe <hi>Miracles,</hi> as <hi>Africke</hi> with <hi>Monſters.</hi> For here hath beene ſeene a <hi>Maid</hi> with a miraculous <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pron,</hi> caſting little flaſhes of lightning in the darke (for this alſo was a <hi>worke of darkneſſe</hi>) and eaſily done by an artificiall tincture of Sulphure. Not long after (which the World gazed at) they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the <hi>Image of Garnet</hi> the Ieſuite in a ſtraw: wherein there was nothing more wonderfull, than that any ſhould account it miraculous, it being (by the confeſſion, vpon oath, of ſuch Recuſants as had kept it) <hi>no more like Garnets face than any other mans;</hi> and ſo little exceeding the power of man (therefore no Miracle,) as that a young youth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the arte of limbing did then draw (and that more perfectly) a number of ſuch like, in the huskes of eares of Wheat, in one day.</p>
               <p>The Booke intituled, <hi>A Declaration of egregious Impoſtures practized by Romiſh Priests,</hi> ſetteth forth whole Pageants of counterfeit <hi>Exorciſmes;</hi> one vpon <hi>Sara Williams,</hi> another vpon her ſiſter, <hi>Friſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21548:8"/>Williams,</hi> a third vpon <hi>Anne Smith,</hi> a fourth vpon <hi>Richard Mayne</hi> Gentleman, a fift vpon one <hi>Marwood,</hi> the ſeruant of that <hi>Babington,</hi> who was executed for treaſon. The <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who are recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as Agents in theſe feats, are named to haue beene Maſter <hi>Dibdaile,</hi> Maſter <hi>Sherwood,</hi> Maſter <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Maſter <hi>Stampe,</hi> Maſter <hi>Edmonds,</hi> alias <hi>Weſton,</hi> Maſter <hi>Dryland,</hi> Maſter <hi>Terrill,</hi> Maſter <hi>Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> Maſter <hi>Ballard,</hi> with others; and in concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all miraculous <hi>Exorciſts,</hi> by the confeſſions (vpon oath) of foure of the parties themſelues that were exoreized: albeit it was proued to be nothing but deceitfull cunning, and plaine coſenage.</p>
               <p>Although theſe and the like pranks haue beene often hiſſed of the Stage, for ſtale and groſſe forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yet notwithſtanding haue they aduentured to publiſh that, which they call <hi>A faithfull Relation of their proceedings,</hi> in exorcizing the <hi>Boy of Bilſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See this Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whole, in the end of this Treatiſe.</note> as <hi>poſſeſſed</hi> of the <hi>Deuill.</hi> Which <hi>Relation</hi> who ſo readeth, ſhall thinke that hee hath ſeene a <hi>Comedie,</hi> wherein the Actors, which preſent themſelues, are theſe; A craftie <hi>old man,</hi> teaching the feats and pranks of counterfeiting a perſon <hi>Demoniacall</hi> and poſſeſſed of the <hi>Deuill;</hi> the next, a moſt docible, ſubtle, and expert young <hi>Boy,</hi> farre more dextrous in the Practique part, than his Maſter was in the Theorie; after him appeare three Romiſh <hi>Prieſts,</hi> the Authors of ſeducement, conjuring their onely imaginarie <hi>Deuils,</hi> which they brought with them; and laſtly, a <hi>Chorus</hi> of credulous people eaſily ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, not ſo much by the fubtletie of thoſe <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as by their owne ſottiſhneſſe; which will hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be better manifeſted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="advertisement">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21548:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The fourth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing, that Romiſh Priests baue thought it lawfull for them, to delude men by forged Miracles, and feined Relations or Reports, vnder ſome religious pretences.</head>
               <p>IF in practiſe of vnlawfull things they were not perſwaded that they may doe them lawfully, there might bee ſome hope that they would at length bee brought to deteſt their diſſimulations: but now that they varniſh their godleſſe forgeries with the colour of Godly intentions, how can we euer expect that they will renounce their cuſtome of lying? And that it is ſo, in ſome Romiſh Prieſts, their owne <hi>Canus</hi> wil witneſſe, where he inueigheth againſt ſome,<note place="margin">eanus loc. Theol. l. <hi>11.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Qui pietatis loco duxerunt mendacia pro religione fingere,</hi> that is; <hi>Who hold it a point of godlineſſe to lye for the aduantage of Religion.</hi> As alſo <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> complayning of others who indeauour to excite men to their Religion,<note place="margin">Eraſ in cenſura ante lib. Confeſſ. Aug.</note> 
                  <hi>Fabulisvanis, &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis miraculis,</hi> that is, <hi>By vaine fables, and feigned miracles.</hi> Yea, and their <hi>Agrippa</hi> putteth this in the Catalogue <hi>of vaine ſciences,</hi> and not without indignation; <hi>Qui piè nonnihil admentientes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponunt reliquias, fabricant miracula, confingunt ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribiles fabulas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Agripſa de van. ſcient. c. <hi>97.</hi>
                  </note> that is, <hi>Who by the mixture of ſome godly lyes deuiſe ſuppoſititious reliques, forge mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and faine fearefull fables.</hi> The like complaint made their <hi>Viues</hi> againſt their <hi>deuout lyes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Viues in Aug. de Ciuit. Dei l. <hi>22.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>We may iuſtly recount among theſe the Romiſh Doctrine of <hi>Indulgences,</hi> which (ſince the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21548:9"/>of <hi>Trent</hi>) is by Pope <hi>Pius Quartus</hi> added vnto the Romane <hi>Creede;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pius Quarlus in forma Inramene.</note> albeit, at the time of their firſt inuention, they were iudged by men learned and profeſſed in the Romane Religion, to be no better than <hi>piae fraudes,</hi> that is, <hi>Godly deceits.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>As</hi> Greg. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. <hi>reports.</hi> Tract de Indu'g. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> And what ſhall wee ſay of their Hiſtorie called the <hi>Legend,</hi> graced with no leſſe a Title than <hi>Aurea, Golden;</hi> which it was lawfull to tranſlate into any language, that it might lie open vnto all people, for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in the fundamentall points of Poperie, when as yet the <hi>written Word of God,</hi> and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Goſpell of Ieſus Christ,</hi> was purpoſely ſhut and locked vp in a ſtrange tongue? Notwithſtanding, it cannot be denied, if we beleeue their owne Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, that <hi>there is not a more abſurd booke than it:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſpen. in Tim. Digreſſ. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> Or thus,<note place="margin">Royard praef. ante, Hom. de festo Sanct.</note> 
                  <hi>By the fables and fooleries whereof the Truth it ſelfe is ouerthrowne:</hi> Or thus, <hi>Wherein there are more Monſters than Miracles.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Canus loc. Theol. l. <hi>11.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>And the counterfeit <hi>Miracles,</hi> by <hi>Exorciſmes,</hi> wrought by <hi>Priests</hi> in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> haue (as their owne Relations doe manifeſt) a double inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to wit, of gayning eſtimation vnto the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and beliefe vnto that which they call their <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Cauſe.</hi> Nor may any obiect, that ſuch forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are wrought by ſome obſcure men, of ſmall iudgement, or leſſe conſcience; for theſe are <hi>Prieſts</hi> who haue their miſſion, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion from <hi>Rome,</hi> being ſent (as they ſay) to <hi>ſuffer perſecution</hi> for the Romane Cauſe: for the which ſome of them are in the Catalogue of their <hi>Martyrs,</hi> as namely, <hi>Dibday, Ballard, Harrington;</hi> who, with the other <hi>Priests,</hi> in acting theſe parts, were of the ſame Faith with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21548:10"/>their fellow Prieſt <hi>Thomſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Declar. of Impoſt.</note> who held thoſe their practizes to be <hi>good,</hi> and the credulitie thereunto <hi>Godly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The fift Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing the falſehood of their former Preſumption: and prouing, that no pretext of good intention, or purpoſe whatſoeuer, can iuſtifie any lying wonder, or yet any falſe Report thereaf.</head>
               <p>VVE haue ſeene what masks theſe deceiuable <hi>Miraculists</hi> doe put on, not onely for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, but euen alſo countenancing their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulneſſe, to wit, their pretence of <hi>Deuotion, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Godlineſſe:</hi> in all which there is a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, which is to them the ſoule of ſuch actions. Surely, if this kind of dealing were lawfull, then might it be vſed, eſpecially for the gayning of mens <hi>ſoules,</hi> for the credit of the <hi>Meſſengers of God,</hi> and his <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or for the ſupreme end of all, which is the <hi>glorie of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But none of theſe ſo gracious and glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences can excuſe them. Firſt, not the gayning of mens ſoules,<note place="margin">Wiſd. 1.11.</note> becauſe it is written, <hi>The mouth that lyeth ſlayeth the ſoule.</hi> Now <hi>Charitie,</hi> by Gods Law, beginneth at a mans ſelfe; and can it then conſort with <hi>Charitie,</hi> that, for the ſauing of another, any man may murther himſelfe? And ſecondly, neither will it ſuffer to intend the credit of <hi>Gods Miniſters,</hi> and the eſtabliſhing of their meſſage of Faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21548:10"/>this muſt needs be not onely damnable in it ſelfe, but alſo damageable to the <hi>Faith</hi> both of the <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>Hearers.</hi> The firſt the Apoſtle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, by reprouing them that ſhould <hi>ſay</hi> of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> that they taught men to <hi>doe euill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>that good might come thereof:</hi> of which Calumniators hee concludeth, ſaying, <hi>Whoſe damnation is iuſt.</hi> And if it be <hi>damnable</hi> to ſay that of any vniuſtly, then is it twice damnable for any to <hi>doe euill that good may come thereof.</hi> Concerning the ſecond, the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle is as direct.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.14.</note> 
                  <hi>If we</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>preaching Christ to be riſen from the dead, Chriſt be proued not to be ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, then is our preaching in vaine, as being falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; and then is alſo your faith in vaine.</hi> Noting, that the <hi>preaching,</hi> and conſequently writing of falſehood doth gayne nothing but loſſe of credit to the <hi>Preacher,</hi> and engender infidelitie in him that was a beleeuer: which are due wages, the one of wilfull lying, the other of light credulitie. Nor yet will it preuaile, that for the honour of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe attribute is <hi>Truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.6. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 8.44.</note> they practize to deceiue by a <hi>Lie,</hi> the right cognizance of the <hi>Deuill,</hi> who is a <hi>Lier from the beginning:</hi> for what <hi>ſocietie</hi> then can there be betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Satan?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, the end of all goods ends, the <hi>glorie of God,</hi> cannot priuilege any mans lie. The <hi>friends of Iob</hi> diſputed againſt him, though ignorantly, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him to be an <hi>Hypocrite;</hi> and their whole ſcope was to magnifie the iuſtice of <hi>God</hi> vpon him: but <hi>Iob,</hi> holding nothing to bee more diſhonourable to God than to pleade for him by a lie, ſtands at de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance with them that ſought to pleade after that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21548:11"/>manner; anſwering, with deteſtation of that Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,<note place="margin">Iob 13.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Will you ſpwickedly for God, and talke deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for him? will you accept his perſon? will you yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for God? do you ſo mocke him? ſhall not his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie make you affraid?</hi> What refutation can bee more emphaticall, or yet more iuſt? for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.18.</note> 
                  <hi>It is impoſsible for God to lye;</hi> and as <hi>impoſsible</hi> muſt we thinke it for <hi>God</hi> to approue or iuſtifie any <hi>lie,</hi> how much leſſe wilfull lying? What then are they to forfeit, who ſtampe a fained pretence, as it were a falſe face vpon a <hi>Miracle,</hi> the act of <hi>Gods om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotencie,</hi> which ſhould therefore haue engrauen on it <hi>Truth,</hi> the firſt attribute of the God-head, the perfect Image of the God of <hi>Caeſar</hi> (that is) that it be a true Miracle?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſixt Aduertiſement;</hi> Diſcouering their doctrine of <hi>Mentall Reſeruation,</hi> which we may iuſtly ſuſpect to be the art of concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their deceits, whenſoeuer they abuſe men by their falſe reports,</head>
               <p>THeir <hi>Mentall Reſeruation</hi> is (as they define it) a <hi>mixt Propoſition,</hi> part in ſpeech, and part in minde: as when a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> being in any danger to be diſcouered, is examined whether hee be a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Prieſt? who notwithſtanding doth anſwere; <hi>I am no Romiſh Priest,</hi> (retayning in his minde this clauſe) <hi>To tell it vnto you;</hi> (or) <hi>that you may know,</hi> or the like: and the latter clauſe of the minde (ſay
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21548:11"/>they) maketh the words, <hi>I am no Prieſt,</hi> (otherwiſe falſe in themſelues) to be true, as it were one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition. And thus they thinke to auoyd the guilt of a lie.</p>
               <p>This Sophiſtrie did Maſter <hi>Garnet</hi> teach in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and practized it egregiouſly in the Tower: and this Maſter <hi>Parſons</hi> did vehemently defend, which other <hi>Prieſts</hi> vſed as a <hi>Gygas Ring,</hi> to become inuiſible to men; that no Examiner could eſpie any of their Prieſt-hoods.</p>
               <p>If they thinke it lawfull thus cunningly to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiuocate, for the preſeruation of their owne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and the bodies of others, will they not iudge it neceſſary, for the gaining of mens ſoules, trowe we? What credit then ſhall wee giue vnto ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, which they ſhall falſly inuent, to draw men vnto their Religion, by ſaying (as they haue moſt falſly done) ſuch a <hi>Proteſtant Biſhop</hi> died in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh faith; or ſuch a <hi>Boy</hi> was exorcized and diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of the <hi>Deuill,</hi> by the helpe of a Romiſh <hi>Prieſt?</hi> Or ſuch a <hi>viſion of our Lady</hi> appeared vnto me, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me that I cannot take the Oath of <hi>Allegeance,</hi> without <hi>mortall ſinne?</hi> To theſe men we obiect, Are you ſo vnconſcionable as to lye thus? They readily will anſwere vs, we lye not, for we did equiuocate. As for example, <hi>He died a Catholike,</hi> (reſeruing) <hi>for ought that you ſhall know:</hi> and the <hi>Boy was diſpoſſeſſed by a Prieſt</hi> (reſeruing) <hi>if diſpoſſeſſed:</hi> And <hi>the bleſſed Virgin appeared vnto me,</hi> (reſeruing) <hi>but only in my conceit.</hi> This being the profeſſed guile and deceit of theſe kind of men, we haue iuſt cauſe not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="advertisement">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:21548:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſeuenth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing that <hi>Mentall reſeruation</hi> is no better than lewde lying.</head>
               <p>THis tricke of <hi>Mentall reſeruation</hi> hath beene ſufficiently proued to be not only a <hi>lye,</hi> but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the <hi>blacke Art of lying.</hi> As for example; If a Ieſuite, being asked whether hee be the true Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of the King of Great Brittaine, ſhall anſwere, contrary to their meaning, <hi>I am,</hi> (but reſeruing in his minde this negatiue particle) <hi>not;</hi> can this make one Propoſition? Is it not rather a Contradiction, and conſequently a flat lye? Let <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelfe ſpeake,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.37. Iames 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Let your yea be yea</hi> (ſaith Chriſt,) <hi>and your nay be nay:</hi> wherein as raſh ſwearing is forbidden, ſo is true ſpeaking co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded. Now I ſuppoſe that none can denie but, <hi>I am,</hi> is <hi>yea,</hi> and, <hi>I am not,</hi> is <hi>nay;</hi> and conſequently that their, <hi>I am,</hi> is alewde <hi>lye.</hi> And that indeed all ſuch <hi>Reſeruations</hi> (as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be qualified with ſome circumſtance of ſpeech, which vnto the intelligent hearer can no way im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that he is no <hi>Priest</hi>) are vndoubtedly a <hi>lye,</hi> hath beene euinced from the teſtimonies of the learned men of their owne Schooles, in a Treatiſe purpoſely not long ſince writ vpon that ſubiect.</p>
               <p>Only I adde for this preſent, that this Arte of <hi>Mentall Reſeruation</hi> tranſcendeth all the wit, not only of Heathen men, but euen the practice of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils</hi> in their <hi>Equiuocations.</hi> For the Heathen, in ſaying,<note place="margin">Cic. Offic.</note> 
                  <hi>Iurauilinguâ, mentem iniuratam gere,</hi> were ſo farre from execuſing this from a <hi>lye,</hi> that they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21548:12"/>called it <hi>falſe;</hi> only they thought it (but erroneouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) lawful for them to lie in ſuch caſe of neceſſitie; when they had to deale with <hi>Pirates</hi> and Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawes. But it neuer entred into the Morall or Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall apprehenſions of theſe great Maſters of Learning, to conceiue otherwiſe of ſuch Romiſh ſecret Notions, than as of very <hi>lies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Deuils,</hi> wee know, did <hi>Equiuocate</hi> in their Oracles, but only by a <hi>verball Equiuocation,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of an ambiguitie of words of double and doubtfull ſignification: wherein although there were deceit, yet was it not by a flat lie, but by an indirect truth. For example, To ſpeake to a man, denying that he hath any money, and to ſay, yes fellow, thou haſt a crowne (meaning, the crowne of his head;) the <hi>verball Equiuocation</hi> is in the word, <hi>Crowne,</hi> whereby the man is deceiued by the indirect, but yet true ſence of the ſame word. Neuertheleſſe theſe (we confeſſe) were called <hi>lying Oracles,</hi> not becauſe of their <hi>verball Equiuocations,</hi> but becauſe thereby they did ſeduce men into Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. But <hi>Mentall Reſeruation</hi> is ſuch a <hi>Cacus' den</hi> as neyther Man, or Deuill by any circumſtance of ſpeech can poſſibly ſpie out.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The eight Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing the meanes to diſcerne falſe Miracles, ly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding the properties of thoſe that are true.</head>
               <p>THere are foure obſeruable properties of diuine Miracles: I. is that the worke of the Miracle
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21548:13"/>be done <hi>Tranſcendently,</hi> by exceeding all power of Nature or Art; II. <hi>Preſently,</hi> without delay; III. <hi>Perfectly,</hi> without defect; The IV. is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the forme, <hi>Sincerely,</hi> voyd of idle Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. Theſe are the true Characters of diuine working, by which if the Acts of Romiſh Prieſts be duely examined, they will be found exorbitant in all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The ninth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing the falſhood of ſuch Romiſh practizes; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not done by a tranſcendent power.</head>
               <p>ALthough the power of falſe <hi>Miracles,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of by our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhall ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times worke ſuch great wonders, as are able <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mar. 13.22.</note> 
                  <hi>if it were poſsible, the very Elect;</hi> ſo that wee muſt confeſſe (with their owne Ieſuite) that <hi>Falſe Miracles are ſometimes ſo like vnto true, that they can hardly be diſcerned;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acofla Ieſ. de temp. nouiſſ. lib. <hi>2.6.19.</hi> Bellar. l. <hi>3.</hi> de Pant. c. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> which (as another of them acknowledgeth) <hi>The Deuill worketh by ſecret, but naturall meanes, yet ſuch as deceiue the ſight and iudgements of men:</hi> Notwithſtanding many others are done only by either naturall, or elſe artificiall workings. As namely all that are not done either <hi>preſently</hi> or <hi>perfectly,</hi> as ſhall be ſhewed. But be it that the workes done by theſe <hi>Priests,</hi> could ſeeme to be done as perfectly as they would haue them, yet can they ſauour of nothing but mans craft.</p>
               <p>To inſtance but onely in that one thing,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21548:13"/>wherein (as it ſeemeth) they ioyntly glorie,<note place="margin">Bellar. Bozius, and the <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Hiſt.</hi>
                  </note> which is the adoration done by bruite beaſts, as namely by a <hi>Mule,</hi> a <hi>cade Lambe,</hi> and a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiffe Dogge,</hi> vnto the <hi>Hoaſt</hi> in the Sacrament. Why haue you neuer ſeene <hi>Apes</hi> and <hi>Babions</hi> ſo diſciplined, as to kneele downe, and make courtſie? Did not <hi>Bankes</hi> teach his <hi>Horſe</hi> the like feates; When to acquit himſelfe of the ſuſpition of dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the <hi>Deuill,</hi> he made his Horſe <hi>Morocco</hi> to kneele downe before a <hi>Crucifix</hi> in France?</p>
               <p>Come we neerer to our <hi>Exorcists,</hi> and ſee their doings, and wee find (by the confeſſions of their owne Patients) that if there be any diſeaſe, as ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Mother, then they call this a <hi>Deuill;</hi> and if there be none, yet through violent and vntempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate working by their hallowed fumes and ſulphu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous odours, which they vſe in their Exorciſmes, they make a <hi>Deuill,</hi> that is, ſome diſeaſe; and after, by ſuffering their ſuppoſed <hi>Demoniack</hi> to take a little reſt, O then behold a Miracle! forſooth, they haue ſtilled the Deuill. I ſhould but take paines fot repentance to buſie my ſelfe, or my Reader with ripping vp the friuolous Wonders, which they haue regiſtred, touching the power of expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Deuils.</hi> If any mans appetite ſerue him for theſe iunkets, let him reade their <hi>Legend,</hi> touching ſuch Maruels, and he may ſoone ſatisfie, yea, and ſurfeit himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="advertisement">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:21548:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The tenth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing (for the better diſcerning of falſe Miracles) the <hi>II.</hi> and <hi>III.</hi> Properties, which is, to be done <hi>Preſently</hi> and <hi>Perfectly.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſecond, which is <hi>Preſently,</hi> their owne Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Abulenſis</hi> hath obſerued;<note place="margin">Abulen. in Mat. <hi>8.</hi> q. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Nullum mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum ſucceſsiuè eſſe factum, ſed ſtatim, quandò Chriſtus illud fieri voluit:</hi> that <hi>Chriſt wrought no Miracle by piece-meale, but out of hand, ſo ſoone as hee would haue it done,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 8.24, 25.</note> What can bee obiected againſt this, but only the cure of him that was <hi>blind,</hi> whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> made firſt to ſee, and after to <hi>ſee perfectly?</hi> To this the ſame Biſhop anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth moſt fitly, that <hi>This may be ſaid to haue beene done preſently,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A'nden. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe ſuddenly, and as ſoone as hee would haue it done.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third, to doe it <hi>Perfectly,</hi> is as well acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be a proper character of a true <hi>Miracle,</hi> whereby <hi>diuine Miracles are diſtinguiſhed from thoſe that are Deuilliſh:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anaſtaſ Cochelet. Palaeſt honor. cap. <hi>31.</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lrio Ieſ. diſq. Mag. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> and that <hi>When they that are cured relapſe into their former diſeaſes, it is a certaine ſigne that it is not the gift of God, whoſe workes are perfect.</hi> Now let vs weigh the <hi>Prieſts</hi> practizes in theſe ſcales, and their workes will bee found too light, as not being done <hi>Preſently:</hi> for theſe <hi>Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſts</hi> labour alwayes vpon their parties poſſeſſed, as Phyſicians doe vpon their Patients, conſuming monethes in practizing their Art, before they can ſeeme to haue finiſhed their cure. So it fell out with the <hi>Exorciſts</hi> at Saint <hi>Baume in France,</hi> at <hi>Denham</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:21548:14"/>in <hi>Bucking hamſhire,</hi> at <hi>Hackney</hi> neere <hi>London,</hi> and at <hi>Bilſon</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then that they are not ſo <hi>Perfectly</hi> holpen,<note place="margin">See hereafter.</note> doth appeare by the <hi>Exorcists</hi> often boaſting, how they driue the <hi>Deuill</hi> (as though it were a running gow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh ſpirit, flitting from one ioynt to another) ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time into the <hi>Tongue,</hi> ſometime into the <hi>Toe,</hi> and ſometime into places, for modeſtie not to bee na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Wherein they play with the <hi>Deuill</hi> only as idle fellowes doe with their <hi>Apes,</hi> making them skip from one place to another; when as the power of diuine <hi>Exorciſme</hi> was <hi>inſtantly</hi> and <hi>abſolutely</hi> to expell the <hi>Deuill,</hi> but not to dally and ſport with him in his hold of poſſeſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The eleuenth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing the laſt note of falſe <hi>Miracles,</hi> by want of the fourth propertie of true workes, to wit, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Sinceritie</hi> without Superstition.</head>
               <p>AGainſt this they erre both in their manner, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and end of working. The manner is by vſing ſome ſet forme of words.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The twelfth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing their Superſtition by their formes.</head>
               <p>THat is worth our obſeruation, which hath falne from the penne of their owne Ieſuite,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21548:15"/>namely,<note place="margin">De'lrio Ieſ. diſq. Magic. in queſt. var. de morb. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand.</note> that <hi>Holy men of former times</hi> [non ſunt vſi formis conceptis, &amp;c.] <hi>did not vſe any ſet formes of words, but ſometime one manner, and ſometime another, ſuch as the Spirit of God did ſuggeſt vnto them: nor did God grant vnto them the gifts of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vnder the condition of vſing any forme of ſpeech.</hi> Which is no more than that which their <hi>Eſpencaeus</hi> will haue vs to obſerue in the practiſe of <hi>Christ</hi> and of his Diſciples. <hi>Chriſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vſed not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny peculiar Ceremonies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſpen. in Tim. Digreſſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>but ſimply commanding the Deuill, by his inuiſible power did driue him out. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet doe wee reade that the Apoſtles of Chriſt did vſe any ſet forme, or ceremonie.</hi> If wee ſhall bring the practiſes of their <hi>Prieſts</hi> to be tryed by this teſt, wee ſhall find that their formall <hi>Exorciſmes</hi> differ but little from Magicall Incantations. For (to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit others) our <hi>Exorcists</hi> at <hi>Bilſon</hi> did profeſſe at their firſt comming to the <hi>Boy</hi> that they could doe nothing,<note place="margin">See hereafter.</note> for diſpoſſeſſing of the <hi>Deuill</hi> out of him, before that they had obtayned a Booke called <hi>Theſaurus Exorciſmorum, which</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>is now at London.</hi> Doe you not now ſee the diſtance betwixt the <hi>Spirit</hi> and the power of the <hi>Prieſt</hi> to bee as much as from <hi>Bilſon</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> that is, an hundred miles at leaſt? are theſe <hi>Exorciſts?</hi> And although we know that the <hi>Deuill</hi> is a great Scholler, yet did euer the manner of Exorciſing anciently conſiſt in Booke-formes? is not this groſſe Superſtition? So likewiſe are their other Circumſtantiall Acts, of almoſt, ſtifling their Patients with ſulphureous <hi>Fumes;</hi> buffetting them with their Prieſtly <hi>ſtoles;</hi> beſprinkling them with pale fuls of <hi>Holy-Water,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:21548:15"/>and <hi>Herbes;</hi> yea, and (whereof notwithſtanding ſome haue not beene aſhamed to boaſt off, as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of the dignitie of a Miraculiſt) <hi>Daemonem po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis crepitu, aut recentis ſtercoris foetore depellere:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>See in their</hi> Coſmus Philiarch. de offic. ſacerd. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> that is, <hi>The repelling of the Deuill with the blast of ſuch a winde, and the ſtench</hi> of ſuch an herbe which I ſhame to engliſh. Which if it were poſſible for a man to beleeue, yet might they conſider the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of theſe fooleries; and vnderſtand that the <hi>Deuill,</hi> that nimble Antique, doth but dally with them, paſſing and repaſſing as Boyes doe in their ſports, when and how hee liſteth: as was diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a <hi>yong Monke obſeſſed of the Deuill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gerard. Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. apud Zuinger. theat. hum. vit. lib. <hi>4.</hi> in Tit. de Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niacis.</note> which <hi>Deuill indured</hi> the application of <hi>holy-Water</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hallowed things, <hi>but</hi> yet <hi>refuſed to depart from the partie obſeſſed</hi> vntil ſuch time as this <hi>Nouice was ſoundly laſht with a Whip;</hi> whereupon the <hi>Deuill</hi> gaue place, and then <hi>he was deliuered.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The thirteenth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing their ſecond point of Superſtition, in reſpect of the ordinarie inſtruments of working, which in theſe latter times are Images.</head>
               <p>THe Patriarke <hi>Tharaſius</hi> in that latter <hi>Synod of Nice</hi> (which was the great Patroneſſe of the <hi>worſhip of Images,</hi> but after contradicted by the <hi>Councell of Frankford)</hi> did confeſſe in the preſence of all the Biſhops there aſſembled, that <hi>No Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were then wrought by Images among Chriſtians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Surius Tom. <hi>3.</hi> Conc. Act. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21548:16"/>
                  <hi>for their beliefe.</hi> But he that ſhall now trauell tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row either Romiſh Countries,' or Bookes ſhall bee ſtored with any Miracles, of whatſoeuer ſort, (put them all together) more than thoſe which are done by the <hi>Images of the bleſſed Virgin,</hi> as at <hi>Lorretto,</hi> at <hi>Hales,</hi> at <hi>Sichem;</hi> where with the Bookes of <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellinus, Lipſius,</hi> and <hi>Coſterus</hi> are ſo fraught.</p>
               <p>But becauſe their <hi>Patriark</hi> durſt ſay in ſo great and generall a preſence of <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Diuines, that <hi>no Miracles were wrought by Images,</hi> except a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>Infidels,</hi> what can any collect from thence but either that <hi>Images</hi> were not ſo miraculous in thoſe former times, when notwithſtanding, ifeuer, (that being the time wherein they moſt of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the <hi>worſhip of Images</hi>) they were to bee exſpected: or elſe that the people of theſe times, which are ſo addicted to ſuch Miracles, are more <hi>Infidels.</hi> How ſoeuer it muſt needs ſauour of much Superſtition that the vulgar people (as appeareth by the complaint of their owne Authours) <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Images moſt idolatrouſly,</hi> ſhould be nouriſhed in their Idolatrous fancies by the pretended <hi>Miracles</hi> wrought by <hi>Images.</hi> In all which maruels nothing ſeemeth more maruellous then the faſcination of men, in beeleeuing them.</p>
               <p>This place required that I ſhould ſpeake of their diuers Ceremonies in their <hi>Exorciſmes,</hi> to ſhew their numerall <hi>Croſsings, Reliques</hi> of falſe Saints, their <hi>Holy-Water,</hi> which they conſecrate both to driue away <hi>Deuils,</hi> and to purge <hi>veniall ſinnes;</hi> beſides other formes of their practice, which are altogether ſuperſtitious, if not alſo ſacrilegious. For
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21548:16"/>(to inſtance in the laſt) what greater ſacrilege can there be, than to aſſume power to ordaine any ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for conferring of a ſpirituall grace of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes? What is this elſe than to inſtitute a <hi>Sacrament,</hi> an act properly and ſoly belonging to the authoritie of him, who is the Creatour of ſoules? But theſe things being obuious vnto all men, I tooke hereby occaſion to inſert the former obſeruation, concerning Images, albeit without Exorciſmes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The fourteenth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing the ſecond point of their Superſtition, by their impious and abhominable Conſultation with Deuils in their Exorciſmes, for reſolution in points of Religion.</head>
               <p>COncerning this I will firſt manifeſt that they vſually practize it; and ſecondly, propound their Reaſons for ſo doing, and confute them.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>That they vſe to conſult with Deuils about doctrinall points in Religion.</head>
                  <p>LEt any man reade the Bookes, or heare the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the Romiſh Exorciſts of theſe latter times, and he ſhall find that there is nothing more ordinarie with them than their familiar conference with the <hi>Deuill,</hi> touching queſtions of Religion. <hi>Cotton</hi> the Ieſuite his <hi>Interrogatories</hi> put to the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21548:17"/>to reſolue off, concerning <hi>Purgatory</hi> for his <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes,</hi> and <hi>Hel</hi> for vs <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> with many other curious queſtions, are more than notorious. The Prieſts at <hi>Denham</hi> in their Adiurations were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, by which they ſought to ſatisfie their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents about the truth of the <hi>Immaculate Conoep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Virgin Mary,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of Impoſtures, &amp;c.</note> of <hi>Pope Gregorie</hi> XIII. <hi>his being a Saint in Heauen,</hi> of the <hi>Sacrament of the Altar,</hi> and <hi>Christs bodily preſence therein.</hi> The Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite <hi>Turſellin</hi> contendeth by all the ſtrength of his wit to giue ſatisfaction to his Reader,<note place="margin">Turſellin. Hiſt. Dom. Laeuret.</note> concerning the truth of the miraculous <hi>Tranſmigration</hi> of the <hi>bleſſed Virgins houſe from Iurie to Loretto</hi> in Italy.<note place="margin">Idem Epiſt. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dic ante Hiſt. Iuſtus Baronius Epiſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Which one houſe of the Virgin excelleth</hi> (as they ſay) <hi>all others that euer were dedicated vnto her. Whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to there is daily concourſe from all Nations of the World, eſpecially from France, Spaine, the Indies, and moſt remote parts by Kings, Princes, and other people.</hi> yet was not the truth of this <hi>Hiſtorie</hi> ſo abſolute in all points vntill an horrible <hi>Deuill,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Turſellin. quo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia.</note> called <hi>Arcto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> was conſulted with, who affirmed that <hi>That houſe was the very ſame place, wherein the Angell Gaebriel ſaluted the bleſſed Virgin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our Romiſh Preiſts at <hi>Bilſon</hi> are deſirous that their Diſciples ſhould know (which is their maine queſtion) whether the Proteſtants or Romaniſts are more ſafe in their Religion: to this purpoſe they aduiſe with their faithfull Doctor the <hi>Deuill,</hi> and ſet the reſolution downe in that which they call <hi>A faithfull Relation,</hi> (and that to vſe their mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall phraſe) as a <hi>Markable thing.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See heereafter <hi>Pag.</hi> 51.</note> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>I</hi> (ſaith the Prieſt) <hi>commanded the Deuill to ſhew how he would
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21548:17"/>one dying out of the Romane Church: which he did by violent pulling and byting of the clothes. Then I would know of him how he did vſe</hi> Luther, Caluine <hi>and</hi> Iohn Fox, <hi>which he did after the ſame manner, but in afiercer ſort. Then I asked what power hee had ouer a Romane Catholike dying out of mortall ſinne? Hee then thruſt downe his head trembling, and did no more.</hi>
                     </q> In all which they ſufficiently manifeſt that their profeſſion is vpon ſuch like doubts, to take their reſolution from the Deuill.</p>
                  <p>But of all ſtories of this kind that (I thinke) was euer committed to Print, that which was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in France is moſt famous: and ſo the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts will haue vs to know, intituling it an <hi>Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Hiſtorie of</hi> their <hi>Exorciſmes,</hi> and dedicating it to the then <hi>Queene Regent.</hi> Wherein they bring in, for proofe of many Articles of their Romane faith, a Deuill named <hi>Verrine,</hi> conſtrayned (as they ſay) by the power of God to <hi>ſay</hi> and <hi>ſweare by the liuing God, that Christ is in the Chalice after Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration; bload, and bones,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Admir. Hiſt. pag. <hi>52.</hi> &amp; <hi>98.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>as when hee was crueified vpon the Groſſe.</hi> And ſo hee proceedeth in that Booke, preaching both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> orall and Theologicall points of Religion vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e end; and all to this end that the hearts of people might receiue ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the <hi>Deuils</hi> Sermons. Where alſo <hi>F. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelis</hi> the <hi>Exorciſt</hi> himſelfe, in the <hi>Epiſtle to the Reader</hi> before the Booke, further ſaith, and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth as followeth. <hi>We are in good hope that this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie will be no leſſe vſefull and profitable in France, than that was of Laon, printed Anno</hi> 1566. <hi>which greatly confirmed the Catholike faith, and conuerted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21548:18"/>many Heretikes, who heard the Deuils ſay many times in an high voyce, that theſe Her etikes were his friends and confederates.</hi> So that wee cannot but ſee that it is their profeſſion to receiue aſſurance of their faith from the <hi>Deuill;</hi> which may bee yet more euident vnto vs, in as much as that they doe reaſon for the iuſtifying of themſelues in ſo doing, which is the next point.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The fifteenth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing the falſitie of their Reaſons, for their conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with Deuils, by their Exorciſmes, in queſtions of Religion.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Adinration,</hi> which they defend to bee ſo powerfull, is of two ſorts, the one is of an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute <hi>command,</hi> the ſecondis of ſtipulation or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, by a formall <hi>Oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Adiuration</hi> by abſolute command they contend to proue firſt by the example of <hi>Chriſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Deuill;</hi> the next by the example of the <hi>Deuill</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt.</hi> The ſecond they labour to make good by vertue of the band of a formall <hi>Oath.</hi> My part and office will bee to confute them in all, as well particularly as generally.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21548:18"/>
                  <head>The particular Confutation of their firſt Reaſon, whereby they vſe to prooue the lawfulneſſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with Deuils, by the manner of Adiura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which they collect from the example of Chriſt againſt the Deuill.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt foundation, which they lay for this, is that <hi>the Deuill is constrained by the power of God to ſpeake truth:</hi> and therefore they may <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate the Deuill,</hi> and receiue from him an <hi>aſſurance</hi> of the ſame truths. This power of God the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable</hi> French <hi>Hiſtorie</hi> doth obſorue in their <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Verrine,</hi> whom firſt they acknowledge to haue beene <hi>ſent</hi> immediately <hi>from God,</hi> by whoſe power hee was compelled to inſtruct men in the truth, to confound <hi>Belzebub,</hi> and other <hi>Diuels:</hi> and, as if there had beene difference of religion among the <hi>Deuils</hi> in hell, and that this <hi>Verrine</hi> (yet by conſtrant) had beene a Catholike Deuill, hee confirmeth to the world many points of Romiſh faith; inſomuch that the <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Exorcists</hi> doe put an <hi>Eoce</hi> vpon him, ſaying, <hi>Behold a miracle vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard off, that a Deuill ſhould conuert ſoules!</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Admir. Epiſt. pag. <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> We may rather ſay, <hi>Behold ſoules</hi> Chriſtian neuer read of before, that would be couerted by the <hi>Deuill!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to the matter. Their firſt ground they take from the confeſſion of the <hi>Deuill,</hi> when hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be <hi>the Sonne of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Matth. 8.29. Mark. 5.7. Luke 8.28.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>We eaſily grant, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> could as eaſily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the <hi>deuill</hi> to ſpeake truth, as he could aske him the queſtion concerning any truth; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21548:19"/>the <hi>deuill</hi> could no more conceale that his <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> concerning the <hi>God-head of Christ,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging him to bee the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi> than hee could deny his name to bee <hi>Legion.</hi> But this being granted, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> could ſo conſtraine the <hi>Deuills,</hi> yet what can the <hi>Prieſts</hi> collect from hence? Their firſt collection is, that <hi>Christ did inforce the deuill</hi> to make this Confeſſion. But Saint <hi>Chryſostome</hi> will deny this,<note place="margin">See this after.</note> ſaying, That <hi>Christ</hi> was ſo farre from deſiring this Confeſſion of the <hi>deuill,</hi> that hee did abhorre the Confeſſor, and preſently inioyne him ſilence. Their ſecond collection from hence is this;<note place="margin">Admir. Hiſt</note> If (ſay they) <hi>Chriſt did extort truth from the deuill, Why not wee?</hi> Which if it were ſpoken of them vniuerſally, as if they had abſolutely the ſame power in <hi>Miracles,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> had, it were an inference very blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous; becauſe as all diuinity doth teach, <hi>Chriſt</hi> had in him, <hi>poteſtatem excellentiae</hi> (that is) <hi>diuine power to the full,</hi> as the <hi>Sunne</hi> hath light; and all others haue it but deriuatiuely from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as is the light of the <hi>Moone.</hi> But to vnderſtand theſe men in their more moderate ſenſe, that whatſoeuer concerneth the authoritie of commanding or countermanding <hi>deuills,</hi> they may preſume to haue receiued it from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yet is it moſt falſe; becauſe <hi>Christ</hi> went out of his owne accord into the <hi>Wilderneſſe</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat with the <hi>deuill:</hi> will you therefore ſay, <hi>Why not wee</hi> likewiſe? Doth not the Lords Prayer teach you not to follow, but to flie <hi>temptations?</hi> To come nearer to you. <hi>Christ,</hi> at the time of his queſtioning the <hi>deuill,</hi> concerning his name,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21548:19"/>(whereof you haue ſpoken) had in himſelfe a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of diſpenſation and permiſſion to ſuffer the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills (they requeſting as much) <hi>to goe into the Hogges of the Gadarens,</hi> and to <hi>carry them headlong into the Sea;</hi> an Act of his owne omnipotent Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice. Dire you aſſume this power vnto your ſelues, of permitting the <hi>deuill,</hi> if hee ſhould aske you, to enter into other mens Oxen, or Hogs, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firme preſumption of <hi>Why not we?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Furthermore, to ſhew you <hi>why not</hi> you, <hi>Chriſt</hi> had the <hi>wiſdome of diſcerning of ſpirits,</hi> to know what <hi>ſpirit</hi> he had to deale with, and that infallibly: but the <hi>deuil,</hi> how eaſily may he deceiue you or others, when <hi>tranſforming himſelfe into an Angel of light,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.14.</note> and pretending himſelfe an Author of <hi>truth,</hi> hee ſhall become but a Meſſenger of <hi>lies;</hi> whereof the Ieſuit <hi>Del'rio,</hi> and other Authors can ſatisfie you by manifold Examples.<note place="margin">Diſq. Mag.</note> Laſtly (to poſe you a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle) tell vs, when did euer <hi>Chriſt</hi> interogate the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill</hi> concerning any doctrine of truth, either Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall or Morall points of Faith, or precepts of life? The onely queſtion he asked him was, <hi>What is thy name?</hi> and the <hi>deuill</hi> anſwered, <hi>Legion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mark. 5.7. Luk. 8.30.</note> 
                     <hi>for we are many;</hi> euen troupes of <hi>deuills.</hi> Which <hi>Chriſt</hi> did to manifeſt the power of his God hend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the whole hoaft of infernall powers. You therefore that thus arrogate his power ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imitate his wiſedome, who neuer conferred with the <hi>deuill</hi> touching any doctrinall or dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall truth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="advertisement">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21548:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſixteenth Aduertiſement.</hi> Shewing the falſebood of their ſecond Reaſon, for the proofa of their power of Adiuration, to conſtraine the Deuill to ſpeake truth, taken from the Deuills adiuring of Chriſt; with the particular confura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</head>
               <p>THey ſet this down for an vndoubted <hi>Maxime,</hi> that the <hi>Deuils</hi> muſt neceſſarily ſpeake truth, <hi>Whenſoeuer the Exorciſt ſhall exact an oath of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils,<note place="margin">Admir. Hiſt. pag. <hi>131.</hi>
                     </note> compalling them to ſweare, according to the meaning of God and his Church.</hi> They doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (neither doe we charge them with it) that the <hi>Deuill, when bee ſpeaketh of himſelfe, is a liar, and the father of lies:</hi> but onely ſay, that <hi>being adiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to tell the truth, hee is</hi> then <hi>compelled to ſpeake truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſtle to the Reader, before the Hiſtory.</note> Their proofe is thus grounded. <hi>The Deuill ſaid vnto Chriſt, Mark. s. [I charge thee by God, that thou doe not torment vs, but ſuffer vs to enter into the herd of Swine:] Wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> may obſerue</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a remarkable point, that Christ being adiured by the name of God, although it was done by the Deuill, yet condeſcended to the Deuils tequeſt.</hi> And thus they would perſwade vs, that by virtue of this band of an <hi>Oath</hi> the <hi>Deuill</hi> is tied infallibly to confeſſe the <hi>truth.</hi> And hence it is that theſe <hi>Prieſts in France,</hi> and they at <hi>Denhom,</hi> and at <hi>Bilſon,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with others, in then queſtioning with <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills,</hi> doe relye altogether vpon the coaction of them by an <hi>Oath.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, concerning the example which they haue vrged, of the <hi>Deuills adiuring</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>name
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21548:20"/>of God,</hi> it cannot but prooue to be either an illogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call argument, or elſe blaſphemous. For wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, whether the <hi>Deuill,</hi> adiuring <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>name of God,</hi> did conſtraine <hi>Chriſt</hi> to ſpeake truth, or no? If they ſay that hee did not, then is it no ſmall abſurditie, to proone a compulſarie charge of a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> againſt the <hi>Deuill,</hi> by <hi>Chriſts</hi> voluntarie anſwer to the <hi>Deuill.</hi> But if they ſay, that the all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration, vſed by the <hi>Deuill,</hi> had power to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by virtue of the <hi>name of God,</hi> to make an anſwer, then is it altogether blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, for what is it elſe, than to make the <hi>Deuill</hi> the <hi>Exorcizer</hi> of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> It had beene well that theſe men, that thus vrge and preſſe their power of <hi>Exorcization,</hi> had remembred that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the <hi>Acts</hi> 19. of the <hi>runnagate Exorcifts,</hi> the <hi>ſonnes of Sceua a Iew,</hi> when they tooke vpon them to adiure euill ſpirits, ſaying, [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,] <hi>Wee adiure you by Ieſus:</hi> but what?<note place="margin">Acts 19.13. &amp;c.</note> It followeth, <hi>The Deuils</hi> in the poſſeſſed partie did violently fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe <hi>Exorcists,</hi> and made them <hi>runne away;</hi> then might they haue learned rather to reaſon thus, That if <hi>Exorciſme</hi> was not of power in it ſelfe by the name of <hi>Ieſus</hi> (who is <hi>God bleſſed for euer)</hi> to driue away the <hi>Deuills;</hi> how then could we ſay that it had power from the mouth of <hi>deuils,</hi> in the <hi>name of God,</hi> to mooue <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> himſelfe? And inferre thereupon, ſaying to themſelues, <hi>Why</hi> doe <hi>wee not</hi> now bluſh that wee haue argued ſo fondly?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="advertisement">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21548:21"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The ſeuenteenth Aduertiſement.</hi> Shewing their ſecond ground, taken from an Oath, by virtue of the band of an Oath of Stipulation (the Prieſts impoſing a formall Oath vpon the Deuill,) and the falſhood thereof.</head>
               <p>FOr in their <hi>Admirable</hi> French <hi>Hiſtorie</hi> the <hi>Exorcists</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">Admir. Hiſt. pag. <hi>186.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>the Deuils, when they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by the Name of God, and by the authoritie of the Church to take an Oath, the Oath bindeth them.</hi> And as if, by vertue of the ſame <hi>Oath,</hi> the <hi>Exorciſts</hi> themſelues were bound to beleeue the <hi>Deuill,</hi> they put the <hi>Deuill</hi> to an Oath,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 206.</note> ſaying, <hi>It was thought fit, that Vetrine the Deuill ſhould ſolemnly ſweare vpon the bleſſed Sacrament, for confirmation of that which he had aboue ſpoken.</hi> But did euer the <hi>Deuill</hi> take ſuch an Oath?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 95, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 239.</note> 
                  <hi>Yes</hi> (ſay they) <hi>hee ſware by the liuing God, that he was conſtrained to ſay the truth;</hi> And, <hi>he moke a ſolemne Oath, with all the properties of an Oath.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The eighteenth Aduertiſement.</hi> Shewing the falſhood of this piece of nice learning, in impoſing a formall Oath of Stipulation vpon the Deuill, and the impietie thereof, the Deuill being no way capable of a formall Oath.</head>
               <p>THe word [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>I exorcize,</hi>] in the vſe of Diuines,<note place="margin">Exorcizare di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur, hoc eſt, per diuina Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolum ad urande expellere. <hi>Aug. de beat. vita.</hi>
                  </note> in Chriſtian Schooles, is not taken for the Impoſition of a formall Oath vpon <hi>Deuils,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21548:21"/>but an allegation of the powerfull <hi>Name</hi> and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie <hi>of God,</hi> to command the <hi>Deuills;</hi> as wee ſee not onely in the example of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> but euen by the <hi>Acts</hi> of thoſe deuelliſh <hi>Exorciſts, Act.</hi> 19. ſaying vnto the ſpirits,<note place="margin">Acts 19.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Wee adiure you by Ieſus.</hi> Now the <hi>forme</hi> of an <hi>Oath</hi> is of two kindes; and accordingly the Band and Obligation is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. The firſt kind is a ſimple <hi>Inuocation</hi> of God, by calling him to witneſſe; and thus the <hi>Deuill</hi> ſware, ſaying, <hi>By the liuing God, &amp;c.</hi> The ſecond is a mixt Oath, by an <hi>oppignoration</hi> and pledge; pawning ſome pretious thing vnto God: thus the <hi>Deuill,</hi> they ſay, did ſweare <hi>By the Sacrament,</hi> and by the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> And wee make no queſtion but the <hi>Deuill</hi> was able to ſweare by <hi>God,</hi> and by the <hi>Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> thereby ſeeming to ſeeke Gods glorie. For what cannot hee ſweare to doe, who can change himſelfe into the ſeeming ſhape of an <hi>Angel of light?</hi> But our onely probleme is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Deuil</hi> be capable of the band of an Oath, or no? Wee thinke wee may ſweare he is not; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the band of an Oath, made only by <hi>Inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> and <hi>Teſtification,</hi> in calling <hi>God</hi> to witneſſe; nor yet of <hi>oppignoration</hi> and <hi>pledge,</hi> which is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and more ſolemne tye in an Oath.</p>
               <p>For the band of an Oath of <hi>Inuocation</hi> conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, betweene the Iuſtice of God, and mans <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.15.</note> being bound by that <hi>law written in his heart, his conſcience bearing witneſſe, and thoughts accuſing or excuſing</hi> him before God. This is the band of <hi>conſcience</hi> towards God, whereby the partie ſwearing acknowledgeth himſelfe obliged
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21548:22"/>to ſpeake a truth, leſt that hee become gulitie of tranſgreſſion againſt <hi>God.</hi> Therefore to impoſe an Oath vpon the <hi>Deuill,</hi> is to ſuppoſe him being a damnable Reprobate, whoſe propertie is to bee moſt, maliciouſly obſtinate againſt <hi>God</hi> and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to be capable of ſuch a <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which is required in an Oath, and conſequently a conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable honeſt <hi>Deuill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>mixed Oath</hi> is not onely the <hi>inuocation</hi> of the ſupreme Iudge and auenger, in a generall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but the addition alſo (for more ſpecialtie and ſolemnitie) of ſome thing elſe, by way of pledge, which is called an <hi>Oath by oppignoration;</hi> as if a Chriſtian ſhould in ſolemne proteſtation, ſweare by <hi>God</hi> his Sauiour, and by the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> or by the holy <hi>Goſpell:</hi> intending thereby the ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his owne portion of comfort and bleſſing by and in them; and forfeiture thereof if hee vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late his Oath (as in all Oathes is implyed a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Execration vpon default) by loſſe of thoſe precious benefits, which he might otherwiſe enioy in thoſe pawnes and pledges. Now as for the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels,</hi> what intereſt can they haue in the <hi>promiſes</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> belonging to <hi>ſaluation</hi> reuealed in the <hi>Goſpell of Chriſt,</hi> and ſealed by his <hi>Sacraments,</hi> who are forlorne of all intereſt in <hi>Christ</hi> himſelfe, crying vnto him and ſaying,<note place="margin">Mark. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>What haue we to doe with thee, Ieſu, thou Sonne of the highest God? &amp;c.</hi> what for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture can they feare of looſing their pledge, which they haue irreuocably loſt, when they firſt apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from God, and thereupon did eternally looſe all hope of happineſſe; being <hi>reſerued</hi> (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21548:22"/>ſpeaketh) <hi>to the chaines of darkneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iude v. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, an Oath being that high part of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious <hi>ſeruice</hi> belonging vnto God, which hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriateth to himſelfe, ſaying, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſerue the Lord and ſweare by his name</hi> (where,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.13.</note> in the LXX. it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by the confeſſion of the Romaniſts, is proper only vnto God himſelfe, as a ſupreme part of his <hi>worſhip</hi>) let them, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of ſuch familiar conference with the Deuill, conſult with him vpon this queſtion, whither hee can be capable of the office of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Howbeit wee thinke it no leſſe than a Diabolicall propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the <hi>name of God</hi> to impoſe vpon thoſe damned ſpirits the band of an Oath, whereof they cannot be any way capable, to performe it truely and internally, by reaſon of the obſtinacie of their wils, and the deſperateneſſe of their ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Thus farre of our particular confuration of their particular Reaſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The nineteenth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing the Confutation of their profeſsion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting with <hi>Deuils</hi> in generall, by manifeſting the infatuation thereof.</head>
               <p>LEt Romiſh <hi>Prieſts</hi> imagine what they pleaſe, of the power which they haue ouer the <hi>Deuill,</hi> to compell him to ſpeake truth; yet this wee hold
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21548:23"/>for a truth infallible, that it was neuer permitted to any to aduiſe with the <hi>Deuill,</hi> about queſtions of Religion, to receiue any ſatisfaction from him, but directly the contrarie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The twentieth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing the falſhood of their doctrine, for conſulting with <hi>Deuils;</hi> firſt from the examples of Chriſt, and of his Diſciples.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Prieſts,</hi> for the eſtabliſhing of their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, in <hi>Interrogating the Deuill</hi> in queſtions of Religion, and power of conſtraining him to anſwere the truth, haue pitched vpon the <hi>confeſsion of the deuill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 5.7.</note> when he called <hi>Chriſt, The Son of God:</hi> And then, <hi>adiuring Chriſt not to torment him:</hi> And after vpon <hi>Chriſts asking the deuill his name.</hi> From whence their collections are in effect theſe. Firſt, <hi>Christ</hi> asked the <hi>deuill</hi> a queſtion: <hi>Ergo,</hi> wee may <hi>interrogate the deuill.</hi> Secondly, The <hi>deuill</hi> ſaid, <hi>thou art the Sonne of God: Ergo,</hi> hee was <hi>conſtrayned to ſpeake a truth.</hi> Thirdly, The <hi>deuill adiured Christ,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I adiure thee;</hi> and <hi>Chriſt condeſcended: Ergo</hi> their <hi>Adiuration of the deuill</hi> doth inforce him <hi>to ſpeake truth:</hi> and conſequently they haue licence to demand queſtions of the <hi>deuill,</hi> concerning Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; authoritie to adiure the <hi>deuill,</hi> to anſwere; and power to enforce him to anſwere nothing but <hi>truth.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it muſt follow that men may receiue
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21548:23"/>their reſolution, in Theologicall points of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from the <hi>deuils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I maruell what <hi>Deuill</hi> gaue them theſe grounds of thus reaſoning, ſure I am they haue no founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the <hi>Goſpell of Chriſt.</hi> For (to anſwere order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) firſt, the only queſtion that euer <hi>Chriſt</hi> asked the <hi>deuill</hi> was this, <hi>What is thy name?</hi> neuer any, concerning any matter of doctrine; whereof wee haue ſhewed the reaſon before. Secondly, the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils</hi> Confeſſion, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>the Sonne of God,</hi> was neyther extorted, nor imbraced by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which we are now to proue. Thirdly, the <hi>Adiuration,</hi> which the <hi>deuill</hi> vſed to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> our Sauiour condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended not vnto, but repelled; for the <hi>deuill</hi> ſaid, <hi>I adiure thee that thou torment me not.</hi> But why ſaid he thus? it followeth in the next words, <hi>Becauſe Christ had ſaid to the deuill, come out of the man:</hi> therefore the <hi>deuill</hi> adiuring <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that hee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe might keepe his poſſeſſion, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding expelling him out of his hold, it is euident that <hi>Chriſt condeſcended not to the deuils ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuration.</hi> Thus by way of Anſwere.</p>
               <p>We are now to retort their Arguments, and to driue their weapon to their owne pates, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, from the example of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that we are not to admit of any colloquie with the <hi>Deuill</hi> in Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſmes, about matter of Chriſtian Learning. The firſt place is <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Mark. 1.24, 25.</note> Where one <hi>deuill</hi> confeſſed <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be <hi>the holy one of God;</hi> a bleſſed confeſſion, but, becauſe a damned Confeſſor, inſtantly <hi>Ieſus</hi> (as the Text ſheweth) did <hi>rebuke the deuill, ſaying,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21548:24"/>hold thy peace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 3.11, 12.</note> 
                  <hi>and come out of the man.</hi> In <hi>Mark.</hi> 3. diuers <hi>impure ſpirits when they ſaw Ieſus, cryed out and ſaid, Thou art that Sonne of God.</hi> but what? it immediately followeth, And <hi>Ieſus ſtraitly charged them not to make him knowne.</hi> What may we iuſtly inferre from all this?<note place="margin">Eſpen. in Tim. digreſſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
                  </note> I had rather your owne <hi>Eſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeus</hi> ſhould tell you. <hi>Chriſt would not ſuffer the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill to ſpeake, no not the truth; to teach vs that wee giue not any credit at all vnto the deuill, although it may be he ſpeake a truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Orig. hom. in Exod.</note> And to this end he produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the iudgement of <hi>Origen,</hi> concluding from the ſame Scriptures that <hi>Wee are not to interrogate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, nor to entertaine any colloquie with euill Spirits, but to diſpell them by Prayer and Faſting.</hi> Wee find the ſame Father thus reprouing and condemning the Heathen Inchanters.<note place="margin">Orig. in Num. c. <hi>23.</hi> hom. <hi>16.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>God</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>will not haue vs to bee the diſciples of deuils; it is better to bee ignorant than to be taught by them: for this cauſe our Lord Ieſus did not vouchſafe to receiue any teſtimonie from the deuill, but ſaith to him, hold thy peace thou foule ſpirit, and depart out of the man.</hi> Wee need no other Comment vpon theſe Texts than that which hath beene receiued from the golden mouth of <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. tom. <hi>2.</hi> hom. <hi>5.</hi> in Mar.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt ſaith to the deuill,</hi> Mar. 3. <hi>Hold thy peace, and come out of the man: As if Christ had ſaid</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>I came not to ſeeke my approbation from thy teſtimonie, but to caſt thee out of my crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? no commendable commendation can proceede out of the mouth of a Sinner: I need not the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of him, whoſe torment I deſire: let thy ſilence bee my prayſe, hold thou therefore thy peace, get thee out
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21548:24"/>of the man; what doeſt, thou in my Houſe and Inne? &amp;c.</hi> So Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> euen ſo plainly, that for me to make any collections from him were but to comment vpon a Comment.</p>
               <p>Yet may we not omit that when <hi>Chriſt</hi> (if euer) had conference with the Deuill in the <hi>Wilderneſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 4.</note> the <hi>Deuill</hi> was ſtill the Opponent, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> neuer obiected or interrogated, but anſwered: to the firſt it is ſaid, <hi>Chriſt anſwered, it is written, Man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ver. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the ſecond likewiſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> anſwered, <hi>It is written,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not &amp;c.</hi> &amp; to the third <hi>Chriſt</hi> anſwered, <hi>Get thee hence Satan.</hi> Wherefore, as <hi>Christ,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſe 10.</note> ſo eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Chriſtian may make anſweres to the <hi>deuill,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeeke anſweres from him; and allow no vſe of Conference with him but that which may put him to ſilence.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtles of <hi>Christ</hi> were the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of their <hi>Maſter,</hi> as wel in practiſe as knowledge, which we may obſerue in the example of Saint <hi>Paul.</hi> and <hi>Silas, Acts</hi> 16. For Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (to vſe the words of Origen) <hi>imitating Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orig. hom.</hi> 16. <hi>ni</hi> Acts 16.</note> 
                  <hi>turning himſelfe to the Spirit of diuination, ſaid, [I command thee in the Name of Ieſus Chriſt go out of her.] Wherein though ſome may peraduenture aske why Saint</hi> Paul <hi>ſhould in ſuch vehemencie rebuke that Spirit; What, did the deuill ſpeake any Blaſphemie?</hi> [<hi>The Woman</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>hauing a Spirit of diuination followed</hi> Paul <hi>and them that were with him, and cryed ſaying, Theſe men are the Seruants of God most High, who ſhew the way of ſaluation. Whence it is manifeſt that</hi> Paul <hi>was not offended at any words of blaſphemie, but
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21548:25"/>that he held it an indignitie vnto his preaching to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any teſtimony from ſuch a ſpirit.</hi> So <hi>Origen.</hi> And indeed Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> did not ſpend any time of conference with that ſpirit, but inſtantly diſcharge their office of <hi>Exorcizing, commanding the ſpirit to come out of the Maide, and he went out at the ſame houre.</hi> An Act altogether repugnant to the practice of <hi>Romiſh Prieſts,</hi> who profeſſedly aske queſtions, compelling (as they ſay) the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils</hi> to teſtifie that which may beſt ſerue for the dignitie of their <hi>Prieſt-hood:</hi> whereas the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> did not daigne, but rather abhorre, and was <hi>grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> at this ſo ſpecious a teſtimonie, that they <hi>were the Seruants of the Highest.</hi> On the contrary, theſe Prieſts doe greatly glorie in ſuch Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies; as among others, the <hi>French Prieſts</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce to heare the <hi>deuill Verrine</hi> auerre,<note place="margin">Admir. hiſt. p. <hi>133</hi>
                  </note> ſaying, of them; <hi>You are Prieſts, it is no offence if a man neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and turne from an Angell of Heauen, and doe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reuerence vnto you.</hi> Compare thoſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent examples, the one holding it an <hi>indignitie,</hi> the other a <hi>dignitie</hi> to receine teſtimonie of their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from the <hi>deuill;</hi> and the diſtance will appeare to be little leſſe than betweene a Profeſſor Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Apoſtaticall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="advertisement">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:21548:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>The one and twentieth Aduertiſement;</hi> Shewing the falſhood of the ſame doctrine, concerning conſultation with <hi>Deuils</hi> in queſtions of Religion, by teſtimonies of Fathers, and neceſſarie Reaſons.</head>
               <p>WE haue alreadie heard the teſtimonies of <hi>Origen,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> concerning this point;<note place="margin">Thyraeus Ieſ. de locis infestie, part. <hi>1.</hi> Maldon. Ieſ. Com. in Matth. Chryſoſt hom. vlt. de Lazare. Tere. de anima. Athan. ad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch q. <hi>11.</hi> &amp; <hi>13</hi> Theophy. in Mat. <hi>8.</hi> Iſidor. Etym. lib. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> abſence from our Aduerſarie Papers will not ſuffer me to inquire exactly into other Fathers: nor ſhall I greatly need it, eſpecially ſeeing the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites</hi> themſelues doe acknowledge, that <hi>ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> ſuch as were <hi>Chryſoſtome, Tertullian, Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius, Theophilact, Iſidore,</hi> doe all denie that the <hi>ſoules of men departed doe at any time appeare</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>in their owne perſons; but that they who take their ſemblance vpon them are verie deuils, who ſeeke to ſeduce vs.</hi> And therefore theſe Fathers aduiſe vs not to haue any buſineſſe with them, or to giue any credit to their teſtimonies, but <hi>to content our ſelues with direction from holy Scriptures.</hi> Which they ſhould not haue done, if that thoſe ſpirits might, by the power of <hi>Adiurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> be compelled to ſhew that they were <hi>deuils;</hi> and that, being knowne, they would confeſſe nothing but truth.</p>
               <p>All which notwithſtanding, the <hi>Romiſh Priests</hi> ordinarily ſeeke to bee informed of them concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Purgatorie, Indulgences, worſhipping of Images,</hi> and other Myſteries of Romiſh Superſtition; which <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and other <hi>Ieſuites</hi> doe endeuour to confirme by <hi>Apparitions</hi> of the dead: when as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21548:26"/>(according to the iudgement of ancient Fathers) the ſoule that it conuerſant in holy Writ will re-reſolue,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that though the <hi>Deuill</hi> (as in the petition of<note n="*" place="margin">Not to omit (which is elſe-where forgotten) that the <hi>Boy of Bilſon</hi> did fayne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to abhor, and to be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with this Petition as with the firſt verſe of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide pag.</hi> 58. 59.</note> 
                  <hi>Deliuer vs from euill</hi>) may come into his <hi>Pater-Noſter,</hi> yet that he ſhall neuer enter into his <hi>Creed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not to ſtand any longer vpon Antiquitie, I would but deſire any one Example of any one <hi>Father,</hi> in the ſpace of fiue hundred yeares after <hi>Chriſt;</hi> or <hi>Hiſtorie,</hi> in the ſame compaſſe of time, recording and approuing any <hi>Conference with the Deuill,</hi> by way of <hi>Exorciſme,</hi> or otherwiſe for ſatisfaction of any Chriſtian in points of Religion. Let vs at laſt reaſon the matter with theſe men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The two and twentieth Aduertiſement,</hi> Shewing the Reaſons which may be produced againſt this perſwaſion of the Deuil; ariſing aſwell from the Cauſe it ſelfe, as from the Euents.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Reaſons of the firſt kind.</head>
                  <p>Two reaſons may ſuffice, if they be pregnant. The firſt thus. If ſuch be the power of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſts,</hi> that they conſtraine the <hi>Deuill</hi> in the <hi>Name of God;</hi> and by the warrant of the <hi>Church,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe any truth that ſhall be demanded of them, by Adiuration; then ſhould there need, for our ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in matter of Religion, no other <hi>Queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> then <hi>Exorciſts;</hi> no other <hi>Catechiſts</hi> than <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uills;</hi> no other <hi>Tradition, Councell, Scripture,</hi> or
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21548:26"/>
                     <hi>Goſpel</hi> than the <hi>confeſsion</hi> of <hi>Deuils;</hi> yea and then the <hi>Decrees of Popes,</hi> which are held as Oracles in that Church, muſt now (for many of them haue erred) giue place to the <hi>teſtimonies</hi> of <hi>Deutls.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I may not except their <hi>Councell of Trent,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> which would not determine the queſtion concerning the naturall <hi>Conception of the bleſſed Virgin,</hi> whether ſhee were originally immaculate; for either great was the ignorance of thoſe Fathers, that could not; or elſe obſtinacie, that they would not ſet it downe for an <hi>Article in</hi> their <hi>Romane Creed</hi> (as they haue done many other <hi>Articles,</hi> as far repugnant from truth) ſeeing that <hi>Verrine the Deuill,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Admir. Hiſt. pag. <hi>205.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>by power of Exorciſme, was brought to ſweare vpon the bleſſed Sacrament, and did anſwer vpon that Oath, that ſhe was originally immaculate.</hi> Albeit <hi>Bernard, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aquinas, Bonauenture,</hi> and many hundreds in the Romiſh Church would heerein haue <hi>giuen the deuill the lye.</hi> It had beene good, before they had giuen credit to this <hi>deuill,</hi> to haue ſought ſome certaine reſolution, how to reconcile the different reuelations made to Saint <hi>Bridget</hi> &amp; Saint <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi> concerning the ſame queſtion: <hi>Katherine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told by reuelation, that the <hi>Conception of the bleſſed Virgin was immaculate;</hi> but Saint <hi>Bridget</hi> informed of the contrarie. And becauſe ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions will admit no reconciliation, it would become them to learne how to diſcerne, whether theſe <hi>Reuelations</hi> came from the <hi>deaill,</hi> as from the <hi>lying Angel;</hi> whereof wee thinke the <hi>deuill Verrine</hi> can be no competent Iudge.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, you that queſtion the <hi>deuill,</hi> ſuffer
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21548:27"/>your ſelues to bee queſtioned in a few words. If the <hi>deuils</hi> be made (as you ſay) <hi>Meſſengers of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine truths,</hi> by the power of your <hi>Exorciſmes,</hi> why doe you indeauour to expell them? Are they but lying Oracles? Why doe you then conferre with them, and not preſently expell them?</p>
                  <p>Many other reaſons might bee added, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince theſe <hi>Prieſts,</hi> by the <hi>deuil's</hi> contradictions in their owne ſtories, euen then, when hee was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iured to ſpeake truth: But to labour to prooue, that the <hi>deuill</hi> cannot lye when hee liſt, and that hee will alſo, whenſoeuer hee can, for a miſchiefe, were to deny him to bee a <hi>deuill,</hi> whoſe propertie is <hi>vel falſum, vel ad falſum dicere:</hi> either to ſpeake that which is falſe, or elſe to a falſe end. What a dangerous thing it was in our firſt <hi>Mother,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine and maintaine parle with the <hi>deuill,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our religious dutie to <hi>God,</hi> all mankind feele by that woefull experience of originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, which they muſt carrie with them to their graues, That which no Aduerſarie ſhall euer be able to refute, is, that the power of <hi>Exorciſme</hi> was giuen vnto the <hi>Church of God</hi> for expulſion of the <hi>deuill,</hi> neuer for conſultation with him, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Conſcience.</p>
                  <p>Thus haue I endeuoured to diſpell this doctrine of conferring with <hi>deuils,</hi> in ſuch caſes, with the ſame zeale as I would wiſh to diſpell the <hi>deuill</hi> himſelfe; and hold it a good reſolution not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue thoſe <hi>Priests,</hi> for direction, in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, who make the <hi>deuill</hi> their ghoſtly Father. Wee chooſe rather to conclude with the ſentences
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21548:27"/>of the holy Fathers of the Church; one directing vs how to auoid ſuch faſcinations, ſaying,<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> 
                     <hi>Non ſtatim, &amp;c. We ought not preſently to admit, of ſuch Acts as are done in the Name of Christ, except they be done in the Truth of Chriſt:</hi> The other deteſting them, ſaying,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Remoueantur illa vel figmenta men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacium hominum, vel portenta fallacium ſpirituum. Away with thoſe workes which are either the fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and deuices of lying men, or elſe the deceitfull acts of prodigious ſpirits.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="advertisement">
               <head>
                  <hi>The 23. and laſt Aduertiſement</hi> Is to demonſtrate the Romiſh falſhood, in <hi>Exorci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing,</hi> by the Euents: which is particularly exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified in a diſcouerie of their Impoſtures, about the <hi>Boy of Bilſon;</hi> not inferiour vnto any of the reſt of their prankes in this kind.</head>
               <p>BVt before wee come to lay downe the naked truth of the matter, touching that <hi>Boy,</hi> and how things ſtood <hi>de facto;</hi> let vs firſt ſuffer the Romiſh Prieſts to boaſt themſelues a while of their miraculous power, in Exorcizing this Child; whom for a while you muſt imagine bee really bewitched and poſſeſſed of the Deuill: that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, by the the euent, may be verified of theſe Miraculiſts, that Scripture, which ſaith,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſe glorie is in their ſhame.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="speech">
               <head>Heare we then the Prieſts ſpeake.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:21548:28"/>
helpe the child was, if they had ſought medicine ſtill in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and not at <hi>Endor,</hi> and of <hi>Belzebub.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt then to ſhew how the Child grew thus to bee tormented, as I haue vnderſtood it of his Parents, and haue heard the Child confirme it himſelfe. The Boy returning homeward, from ſchoole, to <hi>Bilſon</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire</hi> where hee dwelt, an old woman, vnknowne, met him, and taxed him, in that he did not giue her good time of the day, ſaying that he was a foule thing, and that it had been better for him if he had ſaluted her. At which words the Boy felt a thing to pricke him to the very heart.<note place="margin">How the Boy came firſt to be poſſeſſed.</note> In fine, the Boy came home, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed ſome dayes, and at length grew into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme fits, that two or three, (though hee was a child of 12. yeeres of age) could hardly hold him. The Parents of the Child, ſeeing the extremity of the fits, and the miſery and imminent danger of death euery houre the Child did lye in, mooued with tender compaſſion, ſought helpe of <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and with cap and knee, by the meanes of ſome friends, did ſollicit a zealous Gentleman; who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome with their earneſt ſuit, did vſe ſome prayers and lawfull exorciſmes allowed by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke Church, with whoſe prayers the Child was eaſed ſomething, and the force of the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Enemie abated. The Gentleman inſiſting to know how many was in him; to his thinking hee ſaid, Three. Hee (good Gentleman) called away partly by the danger of the place, as alſo by his vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent buſineſſe,<note place="margin">Two others meddied with him ere Jcame.</note> they ſought and ſent for a zealous Gentleman, whoſe zeale and vertues are ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21548:28"/>knowne, yea and acknowledged by Gods ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies themſelues. He moued with compaſſion came thither, vſed his beſt prayers and meanes that at that time he thought conuenient; very much wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened the diuels force, and quelled the extreme fierceneſſe of the fits. Yet hee, within a day or ſo, withdrew himſelfe for the ſame cauſe; yet though abſent in perſon, was moſt mindfull of his miſery. In ſo much as he did negotiate with mee, in that I had been preſent many times in the like occaſions, that I would ſee him, and make tryall whether hee were poſſeſſed, or obſeſſed. I was very vnwilling, yet ouercome by his intreaty, and the former mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, I promiſed him to doe my beſt, and to ſee him within the ſpace of one moneth: yet ſo I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of my buſineſſes, that I came thither in the ſpace of a weeke, about Thurſday before <hi>Corpus Christi</hi> day, where I did finde the Gentleman that requeſted me to come: and finding that they had vſed <hi>Sorceries</hi> of Witches, which made the Child offer violence to himſelfe, wee would not meddle with him, till they had burned thoſe Sorceries ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to him, which they forthwith did fulfill. Whereupon we vſing the reading of the <hi>Litanies,</hi> and the holy <hi>Goſpels,</hi> together with the Exorciſme of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> when I came vnto thoſe words that ſhewed the power that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> had ouer <hi>Simon Magus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The diuell could not ſeduce Saint Peter and Saint Paul.</note> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> on the Magician <hi>Barieſus,</hi> the Child would bee ſo tormented, that three or foure could hardly hold him; which words tooke effect in manner as often as they were vſed. The other Gentleman call'd away, I was left alone,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21548:29"/>till it pleaſed God the Gentleman that had firſt meddled with him, by great chance came thither. He and I both did our beſt, till Saturday about two of the clocke, at which time, vrgent occaſions, though diuers wayes, called vs away: yet wee left holy water,<note place="margin">The vertue of holy water, and of holy oyle.</note> alſo water properly againſt <hi>Witchcraft,</hi> and holy oyle: the firſt hauing that power, that it would make him ſpeake, though dumbe, and his tongue turned into his throat; and the ſecond that force, that being applyed in a little quantity vnto his legs and armes moſt grieuouſly contracted, that a ſtrong man could hardly vnfold them, onely with the force of the holy oyle they would bee ſtretched forth as they were vvont. Wee intreated them in our abſence, to vſe the holy waters and oyle in his extremities, and that wee abſent, would aſſiſt him the beſt that wee could in our prayers; which they continued: on Saturday, Sunday, and Munday, with extreme fits and heauings hee brought vp pinnes,<note place="margin">Strange things voyded.</note> wooll, knotted thred, thrums, roſemary, walnut leaues, feathers, &amp;c. the which he ſtill drinking of the bleſſed water, brought vp: and when hee could not ſpeake, hee would make ſignes for that water, with the letting dovvne of vvhich, preſently he recouered his ſpeech. Well, on Thurſday, being <hi>Corpus Chriſti</hi> day, about three or foure of the clocke I came againe, found the Child in great extremities, continually heauing vp, and in this time he had brought vp 11. pinnes, and a knitting needle folded vp in diuers folds. On Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day next, he brought vp the laſt pinne. I told them that I vvas glad that hee brought vp moſt of thoſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21548:29"/>things in my abſence, that well they might ſee that really they came from him, and that it was no col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion of vs. On Saturday night finding the Boy to my thinking ſomewhat obſtinate; I, before the Parents, wiſhed him not to be deluded by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, but that if he ſpake any thing within him, he would impart it to vs, that wee might counſell him for the beſt. A great while the Child would not heare vs, yet at length hee ſaid, hee would not tell vs before all the company. I asking then to whom he would tell it, he anſwered, to your ſelfe, ſo the others would leaue you: hee gaue mee leaue after to ſignifie vnto his Parents, ſiſters, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thus much: Firſt,<note place="margin">The Boy tels what the diuell and Witch ſay in him.</note> that the ſpirit bade him not to hearken to me in any caſe. Secondly, that the Witch ſaid, that ſhee would make an end of him, and that ſhe would bring in othergates things into him, if it were not for me, whom ſhe called a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh P. Thirdly, ſhee ſaid I deſtroyed all her good things. Fourthly, ſhee ſaid, that though I ſhould helpe him, yet ſhee would haue a ſaying to his brothers and ſiſters. Fifthly, hee deſired mee to tarry with him vntill Munday, for when I ſhould leaue him, he ſaid hee ſhould be torne in pieces: whereupon I, according to the preſcript of the <hi>Theſaurus Exorciſmorum,</hi> did bleſſe fire, and did burn thoſe <hi>maleficialia,</hi> Sorceries, thoſe filthy things that came from him; at ſmoke of which, and the fire thereof being temperate onely, and in a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing-diſh, and the ſmoke onely of Frankincenſe, he would vehemently cry out that he was killed, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and choked; though my owne ſelfe, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21548:30"/>others were neerer to all then himſelfe. At length hee ſeemed greatly to reioyce, and with great eagerneſſe dranke vp the ſmoke, ſaying that he ſaw his Enemies tormented. I wiſhed him then to pray for the Witch, and for her conuerſion from that wicked life;<note place="margin">The markable deuotion of the Child.</note> which he did: then the Child did declare that now hee was perfectly himſelfe, and deſired that his bookes, pennes, inke, clothes, yea that euery thing he had might be bleſſed; wiſhing his Parents, ſiſters, and brothers to bleſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and to become <hi>Catholicks;</hi> out of which faith, by Gods grace, he ſaid hee would neuer liue or dye. On Sunday alſo I exorciſed him, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers <hi>Puritans</hi> reſorting to him, I could not haue conueniency to come till towards night. All which day he had many fits, and I comming to him, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of him that ſtill while the <hi>Puritans</hi> were in place on Saturday,<note place="margin">The force of ill company.</note> as alſo at other times, hee ſaw the diuell aſſault him in forme of a Black bird. Well, I perſiſted in exorciſing him, left him very well ſpeaking and merry, retired my ſelfe, hauing ſeene his meate and drinke bleſſed. They then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter giuing him a Syllibub, the ſugar whereof being not bleſſed, he preſently at the taſte thereof began grieuouſly to be tormented. Yea, though he loued flowers,<note place="margin">The power of bleſſed things.</note> yet if vnbleſt, hee would teare them in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and diſtinguiſh them from other; and vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſſed Raiſins he would ſay were too big for his mouth. I was ſent for, and I had not charged him long, but at each charge I did finde the diuell very much to tremble: I hoping of Gods eſpeciall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance at that time, made the diuell to ſwell in his
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21548:30"/>mouth, in ſigne of his preſence, and to expreſſe firſt by ſigne, how many were in him: which he did, holding vp three fingers. I cauſed them then, one by one, to deſcend into the great toe of the right foot, and at the entring thereof to ſhake it, and to ſtirre the legge; all which they did higher and higher, to ſignifie how one was greater then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: then I cauſed the Boy to ſpeake, who did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that hee would liue and dye a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, wiſhing father, mother, and all his friends to ſerue God: then I called vp the chiefe Fiend, and did demand him to ſhew himſelfe, who preſently puts forth the Childs tongue, and ſwelled the end thereof. Then I (all being Proteſtants,<note place="margin">A markable thing.</note> ſauing one Catholicke) commanded the diuell to ſhew by the ſheet before him, how he would vſe one dying out of the Romane Catholicke Church? who very vnwillingly, yet at length obeyed, toſſing, pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, haling, and biting the ſheet, that it did make many to weepe and cry forth. Then I commanded him to ſhew how hee did vſe <hi>Luther, Iohn Caluin,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Fox;</hi> which vnwillingly he did performe after the ſame manner, but in a fiercer ſort. Then I commanded him to ſhew what power he had on a good Catholicke that dyed out of mortall ſinne? hee thruſt downe his armes, trembled, holding downe his head, and did no more. Heereupon the Parents were inſtant with me, preſently and out of hand to helpe the Child. I told them that I did not doubt but by the power of Gods Church (on which I did onely relie, and not on any perſonall vertue of mine owne) to caſt them out preſently.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21548:31"/>But I ſaid,<note place="margin">A coniecture why the Child might be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed.</note> I did feare that the innocent Child was puniſhed for the ſins of his Parents, which might be for their lacke of beliefe; which is a ſinne great enough, ſince without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God. Yet hereupon I ſaid to his mother, Good woman, will you promiſe mee that you will become a Catholicke, if in your ſight I caſt out theſe diuels in forme of fire? ſhee anſwered, that ſhe muſt conſider of that: then ſaid I, I am afraid this Child will not haue helpe; for, fearing the Child was puniſhed for her lacke of beliefe, I doubted that the cauſe remaining, the effect alſo would remaine. Hereupon the Child gaue a great ſhrieke, began to be vehemently tormented, grew obſtinate, in ſo much that I feared another diuell was entred. I exorcized him alſo a long time: but the diuell with the Childs voyce cryed, <hi>The Lord in heauen, the Lord in heauen.</hi> A long time I exorcized him, but ſtill he was obſtinate, crying out, Father, mother, helpe me, helpe me, ſaying that I killed him: and when I gently ſtrooke him on the head with a ſoft ribbon bleſſed, he yelled forth that I kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, curſing me, ſaying, A poxe of God light on the P. ſaying moreouer, I will neuer bee conuerted; to which word a Proteſtant then by, that had ſeene all, replied, Thou wilt then do worſe. Here I commanded the diuell that ſpake,<note place="margin">The Child being himſelfe, denies all the diuell had vttered by his tongue.</note> to ſhew himſelfe in the tongue, who comming forth as out of a trance, I asked him gently, whether he had vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered any of theſe words? he vtterly denied to haue ſpoken them, asking forgiueneſſe, ſaying, that it was not hee that ſpake them; and affirming, by
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21548:31"/>Gods grace, that he would be conſtant in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Catholicke faith till death. Then I called vp the wicked ſpirit, tooke his oth, that with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling hee tendred to be obedient in all to lawfull <hi>Exorciſts,</hi> and not to hinder the eating, drinking, or ſleeping of the Child. Then it being almoſt three of the clocke in the morning, I retired to bed: the next day, being Munday, I came and told the Parents, that I had tarried there as long as I had promiſed, and as long as I well durſt for dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and as my promiſe to others would permit, but promiſed them to come againe as ſoone as I could. The father then offered me the Child to diſpoſe of as I would. I told him I had no conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient place for that purpoſe; but I ſaid, that if hee would not deale with <hi>Witches</hi> and <hi>Sorcerers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The reaſon why J leſt to come any more.</note> I would come as often as I could. The father ſaid, he would ſeeke of <hi>Witches,</hi> or of any other for help. I being ſorry to heare his bad reſolution, told him that I would not mingle God and the diuell together: and then got his promiſe that hee would not vſe holy water and oyle bleſſed, if they meddled with <hi>Witches.</hi> Yet I heare, that he hath not complyend with his promiſe, in extremities of the Boyes fits, hauing recourſe to bleſſed things, ſaying, he will courſe him with them. Well, the ſubſtance of all this I haue heere written, at my comming away I declared before three Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and the Childs Parents, deſiring them, that if I did not ſay truth in all things, that they would challenge me therein. Then the Child being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a ſounding fit, anoynting him with holy oyle, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:21548:32"/>bring him vnto himſelfe, in ſo much that with a ſtaffe he walked vp and downe; and ſince, hee did eate, drinke, ſleepe, and walke, hauing onely ſhort fits, as I am faithfully informed, yea till ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they entertained many <hi>Witches</hi> and <hi>Sorcerers;</hi> notwithſtanding whoſe helpe ſought in vaine, hee is more grieuouſly tormented then euer before. Here before my departure, the Parents of the child offering me money and gold, I refuſed it, thanking them, ſaying, If they would giue mee 20. pound, I would not haue one penny: Charging them that they ſhould not indanger their owne ſoules, and the ſoule of the poore Boy, in ſeeking vnlawfull meanes. And thus on Munday was fortnight I left him: and the truth of this I muſt ſay with S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>God knowes in all this I doe not lye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus deſiring that all may ſucceed to Gods glory, the good of the Child, and the confuſion of all <hi>Sorceries</hi> and <hi>Charmes,</hi> which in my heart and ſoule I deteſt, I leaue the Parents, Child, and thee, Chriſtian Reader, to the mercy of God.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Iuly the firſt.</hi> 1620.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <hi>Non nobis Domine, non nobis, ſed Nomini tuo da Gloriam.</hi>
                  <signed>Yours in charity, loue, or in any good office, <hi>J. W.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Relation was publiſhed by the Prieſts themſelues, and deliuered by one of them, called Maſter</hi> Wheeler, <hi>into the hands of Maſter</hi> Thomas Nechils <hi>Gent. a Recuſant dwelling neer the aforenamed towne of</hi> Bilſon: <hi>as appeareth by his owner confeſſion, vpon oth, taken before the L. Biſhop of Couen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and Lichfield; and added in the end of this Booke.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:21548:32"/>
            <head>THE EGREGIOVS CVNNING OF THE BOY OF <hi>Bilſon,</hi> in counterfeiting himſelfe to be <hi>bewitched, and poſſeſſed of the diuell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Boy,</hi> being about thirteen yeres old (but for wit and ſubtilty farre exceeding his age) was thought by diuers, to bee poſſeſſed of the Diuell and bewitched, by reaſon of many ſtrange fits, and much diſtemper, wherewith he ſeemed to haue been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely affected. In thoſe fits hee appeared both deafe and blinde, writhing his mouth aſide, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually groning and panting, and (although often pinched with mens fingers, pricked with needles, tickled alſo on his ſides, and once whipped with a rod, beſides other the like extremities) yet could he not be diſcerned by either ſhrieking or ſhrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to bewray the leaſt paſſion or feeling. Out of his fits he tooke (as might bee thought) no ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance which hee could digeſt, but together with it, did voyd and caſt out of his mouth, rags, thred, ſtraw, crooked pinnes, &amp;c. Both in, and out of his fits, his belly (by wilfull and continuall abſtinence
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21548:33"/>defrauding his owne guts) was almoſt as flat as his backe, beſides, his throat was ſwolne and hard, his tongue ſtiffe and rolled vp towards the roofe of his mouth, in ſo much that hee ſeemed alwayes dumbe, ſaue that hee would ſpeake once in a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night or three weekes, and that but in very few words.</p>
            <p>Two things there were which gaue moſt iuſt cauſe of preſumption that hee was poſſeſſed and bewitched; one was, that hee could ſtill diſcerne when that woman (which was ſuppoſed to haue bewitched him) was brought into any roome where he was,<note place="margin">Ione Cocke.</note> although ſhe were very ſecretly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed thither, as was one time tryed before the grand Iury at Stafford: the ſecond, that though he would abide other paſſages of Scripture, yet he could not indure the repeating of that text, viz. <hi>In the beginning was the Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Ioh.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. but inſtantly rolling his eyes, and ſhaking his head, as one diſtracted, hee would fall into his vſuall fits of groning, panting, diſtraction, &amp;c. In which plight he continued many moneths, to the great wonder and aſtoniſhment of thouſands, who from diuers parts came to ſee him. Thus much of his cunning.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The meanes of diſcouering his diſsimulation.</head>
               <p>AT the ſummer Aſſiſes held at <hi>Stafford,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Summer Aſſiſes held at Stafford, xviij. Iacobi R. <hi>1620.</hi>
                  </note> the tenth of Auguſt, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1620. the afore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned woman, ſuppoſed to haue beene the Witch, was brought to her triall, before the R. Worſhipful Sir <hi>Peter Warberton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Dauies</hi> Knights,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21548:33"/>then his Maieſties Iuſtices of Aſſize for that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: before whom appeared ſome ſlender circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which were vulgarly eſteemed ſtrong proofes of <hi>Witch-craft;</hi> but after ſome ſpeech, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting the idleneſſe of ſuch fantaſticall delufi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the woman was freed by the Inqueſt. At what time the <hi>Iudges</hi> were pleaſed to commit the care and (if it might ſo be) the cure of the <hi>Boy</hi> vnto the L. <hi>Biſhop of Couentry and Lichfield,</hi> then, and there preſent.</p>
               <p>When he had been with him at the Caſtle of <hi>Eccleſhall,</hi> about a moneth (much of which time his Lo. was neceſſarily abſent from home) although diuers ſymptomes gaue iuſt cauſe to ſuſpect that he did but counterfeit; as namely, the eaſie and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall beating of his pulſe in his ſtrongeſt fits, his quiet reſt and ſleepe, commonly the whole night long, his cleere complection, and (which plainly tells euery beholder that his tongue lyed in ſaying nothing) his ſwallowing of whole morſels of bread without chewing, his ſpitting forth from him as naturally and perfectly as euer hee could doe in his beſt health, (neither of which could poſſibly bee done with a tongue turned vpwards, and doubled towards his throat, as he would ſeeme to haue it,) beſides, his ordinary comming forth of his fits al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with one kind of lowd and large tunable grone: yet notwithſtanding his vſuall caſting vp of his meate, his much faſting, and lanke belly, his patience, or (as it might rather ſeeme) ſenſeleſſe ſtupidity, in induring thoſe many prickings and violent extremities, without any ſigne of feeling,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21548:34"/>did argue ſome bodily diſeaſe and infirmity.</p>
               <p>Therefore it was, that no experiment was vſed on him, vntill that the iudgement of ſome well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued <hi>Phyſician</hi> might be had, to deliuer in what ſtate his body then was: neuertheleſſe, after a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome expectation of ſuch an one, an occaſion of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered it ſelfe, which required and exacted a more ſpeedy and preſent triall.</p>
               <p>The Father of the <hi>Boy</hi> (an honeſt Husbandman of ſufficient ability, innocent and ignorant of any practice in his child) came with an Aunt of his to ſee him: when, being out of his fit, the Father ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly demanded what might bee thought of his ſonnes caſe, and whether he were poſſeſſed, or not? Whereto it was purpoſely anſwered, that nothing ſeemed ſo maruellous, or ſo much to betoken any ſuch thing, as that at the hearing of thoſe words of the holy Goſpell of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>[In the beginning was the Word, &amp;c.]</hi> he ſtill vſed to fall into his fits. For further proofe whereof, then preſently in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers hearing thoſe words were repeated; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly vpon the repetition thereof the <hi>Boy</hi> fell inſtantly into his fit. Lo (quoth his Father then) doe you ſee? what thinke you of this? This (ſaid the <hi>Biſhop</hi>) doe I like very well; for vpon this muſt I begin to worke.</p>
               <p>The ſame day in the afternoone (when word was brought that the <hi>Boy</hi> did ſpeake) diuers reſort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto him, the <hi>Biſhop</hi> calling for a Greeke Teſtament, ſaid vnto him; <hi>Boy,</hi> it is either thou, or the diuel, that abhorreſt thoſe words of the Goſpel: and if it be the diuell, he (being ſo ancient a ſcholer
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21548:34"/>as of almoſt 6000. yeeres ſtanding) knoweth and vnderſtandeth all languages in the world, ſo that he cannot but know when I recite the ſame ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the Goſpell out of the Greeke text: but if it be thy ſelfe, then art thou an execrable wretch, who playeſt the diuels part, in lothing that part of the Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which (aboue all other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) doth expreſſe the admirable vnion of the God-head and manhood in one <hi>Christ</hi> and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; which vnion is the arch-pillar of mans ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherefore looke to thy ſelfe, for now thou art to bee put vnto triall; and marke diligently whether it be that ſame Scripture which ſhall bee read vnto thee; at the reading whereof thou doeſt ſeeme to be ſo much troubled and tormented.</p>
               <p>Then was read vnto him, in Greeke, the twelfth verſe of the firſt Chapter of Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell, [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] which he ſuppoſing to be the firſt verſe, did accordingly, as he was formerly wont, fall into the paſſion of a trance.</p>
               <p>This fit being quickly paſſed ouer, next was read vnto him, in Greeke, the firſt verſe, being indeed the aforeſaid text [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] yet he ſuſpecting that it was not the ſame text, was not any whit troubled therewith.</p>
               <p>By this meanes was his notable fraud, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, fully diſcouered, in ſo much that he ſeemed to be greatly confounded heere with: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſtaring with his eyes, and caſting his head on both ſides the bed, wheron he lay, that he might diſſemble his diſſimulation the better, hee told the company y he was troubled at the ſight of 2. mice.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:21548:35"/>
               <p>After this diſcouery, (to the end that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> might be freed from further triall, and bee ſent home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to his father) hee complained of extreme ſickneſſe, and by writing, as well as hee could, did ſignifie that he had a great paine in his belly: and the morning following, making water in an Vri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, his water was as blacke as Inke; for there were ſome that writ very legibly therewith. And in the like ſort, two dayes following hee ſeemed to make water of the ſame colour. Which that hee might the more cunningly diſſemble, hee, in the making thereof vehemently groned; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon one comming into the roome to him, the Boy did ſhew him his manner of making water, whereof a little remaine came then from him, of the ſame blacke tincture, which hee purpoſely had reſerued within the skinne, to make ſemblance that it ſo came immediately from him.</p>
               <p>But the third day following (which was the Lords day) by diligent watchfulneſſe, and other meanes which was vſed to obſerue him, hee was eſpyed mixing Inke with his Vrine, and nimbly conueying the Inkhome into a priuate place. When being ſuddenly deprehended in this his conueyance, after an earneſt, but louing exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made vnto him, this deafe began to heare, and dumbe to ſpeake: and at the ſight of his vngracious and godleſſe practices, he braſt out into plentifull teares, confeſſing all, to his owne ſhame, and Gods glory. Which confeſſion (before he had heard of the aforeſaid Relation of the <hi>Priests</hi>) hee made the ſame day, in manner following.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="examination">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:21548:35"/>
               <head>THE FIRST EXAMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NATION, AND CONFESSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON OF THE BOY OF BILSON, NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>William Perry,</hi> taken before the Reuerend Father in God, <hi>Thomas</hi> L. Biſhop of <hi>Couentry</hi> and <hi>Lichfield,</hi> at <hi>Eccleſhall</hi> Caſtle, 8. <hi>Octob.</hi> 1620. touching <hi>his counterfeit practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing examined how long ſince, and of whom hee had learned ſuch tricks and coozening deuices? The Boy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collecting himſelfe, anſwered as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth: In Lent laſt (ſaid he) there met me, not farre from my fathers houſe, an old man, who called himſelfe <hi>Thomas</hi> (but his ſurname I cannot remember) hauing a gray beard, ruſſet apparell, and carrying a cradle of glaſſes or pots on his backe, who ſaid vnto mee after this manner: <q>
                     <hi>Now, pretty Boy, where dwellest thou? dost thou goe to ſchoole? If thou wilt doe as I ſhall teach thee, thou ſhalt not need to goe to ſchoole; for</hi> (ſaid hee) <hi>I can teach thee ſuch tricks and feats, that the people that ſee thee, ſhall beleeue that thou art bewitched, and ſo ſhall lament and pitty thee.</hi>
                  </q> Whereupon I being
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21548:36"/>willing not to come at ſchoole, for feare of whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, was deſirous to learne ſuch tricks. By and by this old man began to teach me, firſt, how to grone and mourne; next, to roll and caſt vp my eyes, ſo that nothing but the white of the eye ſhould bee ſeene, after that, to wreſt and turne my necke and head both wayes towards my backe, then to gape hideouſly with my mouth, &amp; grate with my teeth, to cling and draw in my belly and guts, to ſtretch out my legs, and clutch my hands: after that, to put crooked pinnes, rags, and ſuch like baggage, into my mouth, that I might ſeeme to vomit them vp. And although (ſaid he) that ſome folke ſhall put thee to paine, by pricking, and pinching thee, yet thou muſt indure all patiently. After this ſort hee taught and learned me ſome ſix ſeuerall times pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately in a Cloſe, where none could ſee vs.</p>
               <p>And further, that old man made mee beleeue, that a body poſſeſſed could not indure to heare the firſt verſe of the firſt Chapter of <hi>S. Iohns</hi> Goſpell,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.1.</note> 
                  <hi>(viz. In the beginning was the Word, &amp;c.)</hi> and that therefore whenſoeuer I heard it, then I ſhould fall into my fits. Beſides, hee willed mee that I ſhould begin to doe theſe feats, when it ſhould next hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen that I ſhould be ficke: and that then I ſhould accuſe ſome one body or other (whom I had heard to be accounted a <hi>Witch</hi>) to haue bewitched mee. And thereupon afterwards, of my ſelfe, I did accuſe one <hi>Ione Coxe,</hi> and was once minded to haue made my picture in clay, and to haue conueyed it into her houſe, for the better proofe of her bewitching me.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:21548:36"/>
               <p>Being examined how long after it was that hee began to put theſe things into practice, and vpon what occaſion? Hee anſwered; Not long after, (which was about the Eaſter following) I began to be ſicke, and my father ſought helpe for mee in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places: and then ſome Papiſts did perſwade him to ſeeke for helpe at the hands of ſome Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke <hi>Prieſts.</hi> But my mother did rather deſire to haue ſome learned ſcholer or Diuine that was no Papiſt. Yet at length, by their perſwaſions, there was firſt brought vnto me a <hi>Priest,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>I.</hi> Prieſt.</note> of an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent tall ſtature, with long blacke haire, in a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſuit, his doublet opened vnder the armepits with ribbons.</p>
               <p>As ſoone as he came to me, hee drew a ſtone out of his pocket, and hanged it about my necke, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Latine prayers ouer me, putting alſo his finger into my mouth: whereupon I ſeemed to come out of my fit. After that, hee made holy-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and witch-water, ſaying certaine prayers ouer them, and putting ſalt into the witch-water. Then he gaue me a bottlefull of the one of thoſe waters, (but of which I doe not remember) and willed me now and then to caſt ſome of it ouer my bed; and himſelfe, with a little Iſop, did beſprinkle me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with alſo. Before he went away, he ſaid certaine o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Latine words or prayers ouer thoſe waters, (which to my remembrance) did thus ſound, <hi>Eggſe eggſe atque famulo Dei Gulihelmo ante damnando,</hi> and more there of I cannot remember.</p>
               <p>The next morning (as I remember) this <hi>Prieſt</hi> came againe, at which time (becauſe I lay in a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21548:37"/>lower roome, where many people thronged in to ſee me) they remoued me into an vpper roome, more priuate and fitter for them to pray in, where they continued and vſed the like meanes towards me, as they had done before, betwixt a fortnight and three weekes ſpace, during which time I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued my wonted fits. Then at laſt, this Prieſt ſaid that he could not helpe me, becauſe hee wanted a booke, which hee ſent for vp to <hi>London:</hi> but after that the book was brought, he then ſaid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he could not helpe me, without the aide of another Prieſt, whom after that he brought with him.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Prieſt.</note> Hee was a ſhort big fat man, with blackiſh long curled haire, in a kind of ruſſet coloured ſuite, with a ſword by his ſide. As ſoone as he ſaw me, he ſaid, that by the helpe of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>our Lady,</hi> and the <hi>holy Saints</hi> of heauen, he would either caſt the Diuell out of mee that night, or elſe it ſhould goe hard. And firſt, hee drew out a little booke of the bigneſſe of a <hi>Pueriles,</hi> in which he continued praying, til about 11. a clock. of the night, and caſting holy-water on me.</p>
               <p>Then both theſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> went away, but came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto me in the morning, and then they made as much holy-water as a pale could hold. But in the end they confeſſed that they could doe mee no good, without the helpe of a third Prieſt, whom they did ſend for by a Weauer of our towne.</p>
               <p>About a weeke after came the third <hi>Prieſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>III.</hi> Prieſt.</note> being a reaſonable tall old man, in a horſemans coat, with long head-haire: before hee came to our houſe, he did ſay to the man that fetcht him (as I did heare) that if the ſpirits came to me, then I was
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21548:37"/>obſeſt; but if they were within me, then I was poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt. The big fat <hi>Priest</hi> came in with this laſt <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and firſt hee put his finger into my mouth, and ſaid, that I was bewitched at the tongues end: wherfore he bade me drink three or foure draughts of holy-water, which I did: he taught mee alſo to pray to the <hi>Virgin Mary,</hi> and to my <hi>good Angel,</hi> and to all the <hi>Saints</hi> in heauen to helpe me. Then he waſhed my head, feet, and belly with the ſame water, ſaying now and then to mee, <hi>Thou art now ſomewhat better, Boy?</hi> and I would ſay, <hi>Yes, a little better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the ſame time, my father comming one day home before ſupper, he asked mee what I had ſeene in my fits? and I told him that a thing came to me in the likeneſſe of a Black-bird. And now the Prieſt that came laſt vnto me, went out of towne, theſe three Prieſts hauing bin with me about three weekes, but could doe me no good.</p>
               <p>About a weeke after,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Prieſt.</note> came the big fat <hi>Prieſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and held on his former courſe, ſaying, that by. Gods grace he would helpe me. About which time hee made a Sermon to certaine Catholickes which were with me, hauing a white Surpleſſe on him, with a ſtole (as I remember they called it) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his necke: his Text was, <hi>My fleſh is bread in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and my blood is drinke indeed.</hi> After his Sermon, he prayed with me as he had vſed to doe: and then made another paleful of holy-water, wiſhing them to boyle certaine herbs in water, to waſh mee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; as Time, Iſop, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>Vpon the Sunday following, people came in ſo
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21548:38"/>thicke to ſee me, that the <hi>Prieſt</hi> durſt not preach; and he intended to be gone the next day.</p>
               <p>His faſhion was, to bleſſe and croſſe all the meat which both themſelues and I did eate: ſo that when my mother once gaue mee ſome of a Sylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub, which the Pr. had not croſſed in the ſame manner, he told them that there was a <hi>Puritan ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> entred into it.</p>
               <p>Theſe three Prieſts dealt with mee at ſundry times, that I ſhould confeſſe my ſins vnto them: which I did ſometimes, when I liſted to ſpeake, but that was but now and then. They wiſhed mee alſo to turne to their religion, and that then I ſhould haue helpe.</p>
               <p>Vpon that Sunday night before that this fat <hi>Prieſt</hi> was to goe away, he ſaid, that by the helpe of the bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> and the <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints</hi> in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, he would caſt the Diuell out of me.</p>
               <p>A little after, he began to aske certaine queſtions of the <hi>ſpirit</hi> within me; as firſt, what ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the <hi>Puritans</hi> when they dyed? and he told me, that if they went to hell, then the ſpirit ſhould tug and ſhake the bed-clothes: which I did doe after the ſame manner he bade me. Next, he asked what ſhould become of the Roman <hi>Catholickes,</hi> and if they ſhould goe to heauen? that then, in ſigne thereof, I ſhould lift vp my hands, which I did alſo.</p>
               <p>Then the <hi>Prieſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>Come out of thy fits, Will, in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt:</hi> whereupon I ſeemed to come out of a fit, and then hee prayed by mee, and ſaid, that hee would caſt three diuels out of me that night. And
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21548:38"/>ſo he hanged about my necke, and put vnder mine arme a fine ſtole, wrought with great ſiuer letters: and with the one end thereof, being very hard, hee did beate me about the head and face, vntill to my thinking hee made mee blacke and blue; chafing &amp; rubbing my neck with that ſtole, which was ſo rough, that it made my necke very ſore: and ſtill he ſpake to the ſpirits within me, thus; <hi>Come out, you Rogues, you Villaines, I charge you by God and the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin, and by all the Angels and Saints in heauen, that you ſuffer the Boy to eate, and ſleepe:</hi> and withall, he ſtamped with his feet, as he ſpake thoſe words.</p>
               <p>Then he told my father that he would throw out thoſe three ſpirits one after another, ſo that they ſhould plainly ſee them come forth. And if hee ſhould doe ſo, hee asked my mother whether ſhee would become a <hi>Catholicke,</hi> or no? She anſwered him that ſhe would conſider of it. Then, ſaid he, wil I alſo conſider whether I will helpe your ſonne, or no.</p>
               <p>But yet the <hi>Prieſt</hi> continued as he had begun, and ſaid vnto me, <hi>If there be three Diuels in thee, then giue three knocks, in ſigne thereof;</hi> and ſo I did: but at the biggeſt Diuell hee willed me to giue the greateſt thumpe, which I did at the laſt. And ſtill the Prieſt did beate me with his ſtoale, &amp; ſo continued with me til about three of the clocke in the morning: during which time, certaine Papiſts were ſent to pray with me, bringing hallowed candles with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time, the <hi>Prieſt</hi> tooke ſuch<note n="*" place="margin">Viz Crooked pins, rags, ſtraw, &amp;c. and ſuch things as the <hi>Boy</hi> could ſinde and ſteale, into his mouth; as he did once halſe a knitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>needle.</note> things as I had ſeemed to vomit, and burning them with Frankincenſe, hee tooke an old ruſty ſword, and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21548:39"/>ſaid a Latine prayer, reſembling it to the ſword wherwith <hi>Peter</hi> did cut off <hi>Malchus</hi> his eare: he alſo did beate the ſame things with an hammer, beto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening that hammer which nailed <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>The morning being come, the <hi>Prieſt</hi> was to bee gone, and then my father ſaid vnto him, Sir, I ſee you can doe my Child no good, and therfore I muſt ſeeke for ſome other helpe. Yes (ſaid the Prieſt) you will goe ſeeke for helpe at witches to eaſe his body, but you care not for damning his ſoule. But yet before he went away, hee did hallow more water, and then he departed.</p>
               <p>And here the <hi>Boy</hi> was ſuffered to pawſe, and repoſe himſelfe, by reaſon of his weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and was not then further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined till the next time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="examination">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:21548:39"/>
               <head>THE SECOND EX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AMINATION, AND ANSWERE of the ſaid <hi>William Perry,</hi> made vnto certaine other queſtions, which (vpon iuſt and ſpecial <hi>preſumptions</hi>) <hi>were propounded vnto him by the Reuerend Father in God,</hi> THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS, <hi>Lord B. of</hi> Couentry <hi>and</hi> Lichſield, <hi>taken at</hi> Eccleſhall <hi>Caſtle, the</hi> 13. <hi>day of Octob. Anno Dom.</hi> 1620.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, it was demanded of him,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that ſeeing the old man (called <hi>Thomas</hi>) perſwaded him that at length hee ſhould be cured by ſome Popiſh Prieſt; whether hee meant not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly in the end to ſeeme to bee diſpoſſeſſed by ſome, or one ſuch of them?</p>
               <p>He anſwereth, yes; and further, that thereupon he meant to become a Papiſt.</p>
               <p>Secondly, being asked, that if hee did meane ſo,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> why then he would not, after ſo long a time, and ſo great paines taken about him by thoſe Prieſts, yeeld to their <hi>Exorciſmes,</hi> and ſeeme to bee diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by their meanes?</p>
               <p>Hee anſwereth, becauſe that much people did
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21548:40"/>reſort vnto him, and brought him many good things; as alſo for that he was not willing to goe to ſchoole againe: yet that in the end his meaning was to be holpen by them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> being asked that after hee ſaw himſelfe halfe diſcouered, whether in his griefe and feare that all ſhould come to light, he had not an intent to doe himſelfe ſome bodily miſchieſe?</p>
               <p>He anſwereth, that he had; for (ſaith he) the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell had<note n="*" place="margin">It was his owne word.</note> ſteeled my heart, ſo that I cared not to hang my ſelfe; and had purpoſed to doe ſo one night, but that I was watched, and hindred.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> being asked how it could be thought that he ſhould be moued by any Papiſt, to charge a woman for bewitching him, which was her ſelfe an obſtinate <hi>Recuſant?</hi> He anſwereth, that hee was moued by <hi>Thomas</hi> the old man, to lay it on ſome woman ſo ſuſpected: but that onely of himſelfe, without the perſwaſion of any other, he named this<note n="*" place="margin">Ione Cocke.</note> woman; becauſe ſhe was a woman ill thought of, and ſuſpected for ſuch like things.</p>
               <p>Being here put in mind of the deſire,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly before his diſcouery he had to be prayed for, as was accordingly then done, but (as at the ſame time was told him) not to driue the Diuell out of his body, but onely out of his ſoule, wherin the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell had poſſeſſed him, by a diuelliſh obſtinacy of his heart, in faining himſelfe to be bodily poſſeſſed of the diuell: And being further wiſhed to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how that after thoſe prayers he writ on a paper, that he had found much eaſe thereby: He was here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon demanded, whether he did not as then intend
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21548:40"/>and reſolue with himſelfe to make an end of his former courſe, and counterfeit practices; and ſeeme to be diſpoſſeſſed by ſuch prayers?</p>
               <p>He anſwereth, that it was indeed in his minde to doe ſo, becauſe hee had then wearied himſelfe with diſſembling ſo long, and was alſo in feare to be diſcouered and found out.</p>
               <p>And albeit this was eaſily diſcerned to haue bin his reſolution, yet (as was at that time told him) it became not the Profeſſors of <hi>truth</hi> to imitate the Popiſh <hi>Prieſts</hi> in ſuch caſes, who falſly arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated to themſelues ſuch an <hi>Apoſtolicall</hi> power, by <hi>Exorcizing</hi> to expell <hi>Diuels,</hi> although it might (in mans opinion) much worke for the glorifying of <hi>God,</hi> edifying of Chriſtian people in our Church, and alſo for the conuerting of Romiſh Recuſants vnto our true Religion; becauſe this ought to bee the profeſſion of Chriſtians, to ſeeke to glorifie Him onely by <hi>truth,</hi> who will bee worſhipped <hi>in ſpirit and truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here was an end made of examining the <hi>Boy</hi> any further.</p>
               <closer/>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Examinat'. coram praefat'.</hi> R<hi rend="sup">do</hi> 
                     <hi>Patre dictis diebus, anno, &amp; loco; Praeſente Ryc. Baddeley, Notario Publico.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:21548:41"/>
               <head>THE BOY OF BILSON, his priuate and publike Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow after thoſe Popiſh<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bilſon</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> is a Chappelrie within the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Iuriſdiction of <hi>Wooluer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hampto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> where ſacrilegious im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piely hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ſuch ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, that it is much inſected with Popery, &amp; inſested with Popiſh <hi>Prieſts,</hi> whoſe ordinary <hi>Rendeuouz</hi> it is. No maruell therefore if they made choyce thereof, as the filleſt neſt wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to lay and exclude their addle and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſititious egs of politicke impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and <hi>god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deceits.</hi> But this Cockatrice was cruſht in in the ſhell, and their viperous diſſeine thereby deſeated.</note> Prieſts were departed, and had left the Boy (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is confeſſed, and ſet downe) his Father ſought for further helpe by the meanes of <hi>Witches,</hi> (but as wickedly, ſo all in vaine) vntill ſuch time as he was brought from the towne of <hi>Bilſon</hi> aforeſaid, vnto <hi>Lichfield,</hi> before Doctor <hi>Maſter</hi> Chancellor of the Dioces; where he continued vntill hee was carried to the Aſſizes at <hi>Stafford,</hi> and there by the <hi>Iudges</hi> referred and left vnto the aboue-named Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, the I. <hi>Biſhop</hi> of the Dioceſſe; who after a very ſhort time ſent to <hi>Bilſon</hi> for him, and after his arriuall did deale with him, as former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this diſcourſe hath been related.</p>
               <p>Since which time, the <hi>Boy,</hi> vpon laying to his charge the hainouſneſſe of that his offence, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing blaſphemous, in reſpect of <hi>Christ,</hi> whoſe words in the <hi>Goſpell</hi> he fained himſelſe to abhorre; and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelliſh, in reſpect of the <hi>Diuell,</hi> whoſe perſon hee would ſeeme to bee poſſeſſed of; and alſo murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, in reſpect of the poore <hi>Woman,</hi> whom he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly occaſioned to bee brought (as much as in him lay) to the poynt of death: He hath earneſtly
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21548:41"/>bewailed theſe his ſinnes, and (as after his firſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination) by prayer coneiued by himſelfe, to ſuch purpoſe, craued forgiueneſſe at Gods hand for the ſame.</p>
               <p>So hauing continued at <hi>Eccleſhall Caſtle</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, vntill he was perfectly recouered of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer weakneſſe, and benummed limmes, and that his Parents were willing to diſpoſe of him other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, hee was finally brought againe to the laſt Summer-Aſſizes held at <hi>Stafford,</hi> the 26. of Iuly,<note place="margin">Summer Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes held at Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, <hi>19.</hi> Iacobi R. <hi>1621.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1621. where before Sir <hi>Peter Warburton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Humfrey Winch</hi> Knights, his Maieſties Iuſtices of Aſſize, and the face of the County and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey there aſſembled, the <hi>Boy</hi> craued pardon firſt of Almighty <hi>God,</hi> then deſired the <hi>Woman</hi> there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo preſent, to forgiue him; and laſtly, requeſted the whole <hi>Countrey,</hi> whom hee had ſo notoriouſly and wickedly ſcandalized, to admit of that his ſo hearty Confeſſion, for their ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>And thus it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to open the eyes of this <hi>Boy</hi> (that I may ſo ſay) <hi>luto,</hi> with the clay of the Romiſh <hi>Prieſts</hi> lewd impoſtures; and <hi>ſputo,</hi> with the ſpittle of his owne infamy, to ſee his errors, and to glorifie the <hi>God of truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gloriaſoli Deo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:21548:42"/>
               <head>THE EXAMINATION AND ANSWERE OF THOMAS NECHILS of <hi>Nechils,</hi> in the County of <hi>Stafford,</hi> Gentleman (a Recuſant) taken vpon oath before <hi>the R. Reuerend Father in God</hi> THOMAS <hi>L.</hi> Biſhop <hi>of</hi> Couentry <hi>and</hi> Lichfield, <hi>at</hi> Eccleſhall <hi>Caſtle, the</hi> 17. <hi>of</hi> Octob. Anno 1620. <hi>touching the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned</hi> Relation <hi>of the</hi> Prieſts, <hi>of their proceedings with the</hi> Boy of Bilſon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing examined whether hee knew a written diſcourſe then ſhewed vnto him, touching the <hi>Boy of Bilſon,</hi> enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled and beginning thus; <hi>A faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Relation of the proceedings of &amp;c.</hi> and ending in theſe words, <hi>Yours in charity, loue, or any good office?</hi> Hee anſwereth, that hee doth very well know, and remember the ſame.</p>
               <p>Being examined how hee came firſt by that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, or <hi>Relation,</hi> and from whom he had it? Hee anſwereth, that it was deliuered vnto him by a Gentleman, whom he met iourneying on the way towards <hi>Lichfield,</hi> whoſe name was Maſter <hi>Wheeler,</hi> as he told this Examinate. And, being further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, he ſaith that he was as a man of a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21548:42"/>ſtature, round faced, about fiftie yeeres old, and of a blackiſh complection.</p>
               <p>Being examined what further diſcourſe did at that time paſſe betwixt them two, touching the ſaid <hi>Boy,</hi> called <hi>VVilliam Perry?</hi> He anſwereth that the ſaid Maſter <hi>Wheeler</hi> then told this Examinate, that he would acquaint him with the whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, concerning that <hi>Boy:</hi> whereupon hee gaue this Examinate a copie of the afore-named diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe or <hi>Relation</hi> (hauing two copies at the ſame time about him) and willed this Examinate to get it copied out, and to giue one copie thereof vnto one <hi>Philip Higgins</hi> of <hi>Weſtbromage</hi> Yeoman (as hee this Examinate remembers.) And further, that the ſaid Maſter <hi>Wheeler</hi> ſaid vnto this Examinate, that was no matter who ſhould ſee it.</p>
               <p>Being further examined what the ſaid Maſter <hi>Wheeler</hi> did at the ſame time acquaint this Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate with, touching himſelfe? Hee confeſſeth that he told him how that he did often vſe to reſort vnto the French Embaſſadour: that hee did know the <hi>Biſhop of Couentry and Lichfield;</hi> and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that he was knowne to the <hi>Lord Archbiſhop of Canterbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Tho. Nechils.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>
               <hi>Examinat'. coram praefat'.</hi> R<hi rend="sup">do</hi> 
               <hi>Patre dictis die, anno, &amp; loco; Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente Ryc. Baddeley Notario Publ.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
